<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://estebanmoro.org/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>List of Publications</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/list-of-publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/list-of-publications/</guid>
      <description>I have published 105 articles/preprints  2025   Using human mobility data to quantify experienced urban inequalities
Fengli Xu, Qi Wang, Esteban Moro, Lin Chen, Arianna Salazar Miranda, Marta C Gonzalez, Michele Tizzoni, Chaoming Song, Carlo Ratti, Luis Bettencourt, others
Nature Human Behaviour NA 1–11 (2025)
PDF Journal  Worse Weather Amplifies Social Media Activity
Kelton Minor, Esteban Moro, Nick Obradovich
Psychological Science NA 09567976241306099 (2025)
PDF Journal  Human mobility is well described by closed-form gravity-like models learned automatically from data</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using human mobility data to quantify experienced urban inequalities</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-02-26-using-human-mobility-data-to-quantify-experienced-urban-inequalities/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-02-26-using-human-mobility-data-to-quantify-experienced-urban-inequalities/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Fengli Xu, Qi Wang, Esteban Moro, Arianna Salazar Miranda, Marta C. González, Chaoming Song, Carlo Ratti, Luis Bettencourt, James Evans
Publication: Nature Human Behavior (2025) LINK
Abstract: The lived experience of urban life is shaped by personal mobility through dynamic relationships and resources, marked not only by access and opportunity, but also inequality and segregation. The recent availability of fine-grained mobility data and context attributes ranging from venue type to demographic mixture offer researchers a deeper understanding of experienced inequalities at scale, and pose many new questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human mobility is well described by closed-form gravity-like models learned automatically from data</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-02-26-human-mobility-is-well-described-by-closed-form-gravity-like-models-learned-automatically-from-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-02-26-human-mobility-is-well-described-by-closed-form-gravity-like-models-learned-automatically-from-data/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Oriol Cabanas-Tirapu, Lluís Danús, Esteban Moro, Marta Sales-Pardo &amp;amp; Roger Guimerà Publication: Nature Communications 16, 1336 (2025). LINK
Abstract: Modeling human mobility is critical to address questions in urban planning, sustainability, public health, and economic development. However, our understanding and ability to model flows between urban areas are still incomplete. At one end of the modeling spectrum we have gravity models, which are easy to interpret but provide modestly accurate predictions of flows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behaviour-based dependency networks between places shape urban economic resilience</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-01-11-behaviour-based-dependency-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-01-11-behaviour-based-dependency-networks/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Takahiro Yabe, Bernardo García Bulle Bueno, Morgan R Frank, Alex Pentland, Esteban Moro Publication: Nature Human Behavior (2024) LINK
Abstract: Disruptions, such as closures of businesses during pandemics, not only affect businesses and amenities directly but also influence how people move, spreading the impact to other businesses and increasing the overall economic shock. However, it is unclear how much businesses depend on each other during disruptions. Leveraging human mobility data and same-day visits in five US cities, we quantify dependencies between points of interest encompassing businesses, stores and amenities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing human mobility research with open and standardized datasets</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-07-15-enhancing-human-mobility-research-with-open-and-standardized-datasets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-07-15-enhancing-human-mobility-research-with-open-and-standardized-datasets/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Takahiro Yabe, Massimiliano Luca, Kota Tsubouchi, Bruno Lepri, Marta C. Gonzalez &amp;amp; Esteban Moro Publication: Nature Computational Science (2024). doi: 10.1038/s43588-024-00650-3 LINK
Abstract: Human mobility research intersects with various disciplines, with profound implications for urban planning, transportation engineering, public health, disaster management, and economic analysis. Here, we discuss the urgent need for open and standardized datasets in the field, including current challenges and lessons from other computational science domains, and propose collaborative efforts to enhance the validity and reproducibility of human mobility research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estudiar ciudades como sistemas complejos</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-07-15-estudiar-ciudades-como-sistemas-complejos-esteban-moro-en-entrevista-para-c3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-07-15-estudiar-ciudades-como-sistemas-complejos-esteban-moro-en-entrevista-para-c3/</guid>
      <description>Video of my interview about the complexity of Urban Systems at the Centro de Ciencias de la Complejidad (C3) de la Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social media sensors as early signals of influenza outbreaks at scale</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-07-15-social-media-sensors-as-early-signals-of-influenza-outbreaks-at-scale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-07-15-social-media-sensors-as-early-signals-of-influenza-outbreaks-at-scale/</guid>
      <description>Authors: David Martín-Corral, Manuel García-Herranz, Manuel Cebrián &amp;amp; Esteban Moro Publication: EPJ Data Science (2024) 13:43 LINK
Abstract: Detecting early signals of an outbreak in a viral process is challenging due to its exponential nature, yet crucial given the benefits to public health it can provide. If available, the network structure where infection happens can provide rich information about the very early stages of viral outbreaks. For example, more central nodes have been used as social network sensors in biological or informational diffusion processes to detect early contagious outbreaks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infrequent activities predict economic outcomes in major American cities</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-03-23-infrequent-activities-predict-economic-outcomes-in-major-american-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-03-23-infrequent-activities-predict-economic-outcomes-in-major-american-cities/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Shenhao Wang, Yunhan Zheng, Guang Wang, Takahiro Yabe, Esteban Moro &amp;amp; Alex ‘Sandy’ Pentland Publication: Nature Cities 10.1038/s44284-024-00051-7. LINK
Abstract: Many studies have revealed the predictive power of the most frequent, regular and habitual mobility patterns. However, it remains unclear which components of the mobility patterns contain the most informative signals for predicting disparate economic development across urban areas. Here we use machine learning to predict economic outcomes by analyzing the heterogeneous mobility networks of 687 activities from more than 560,000 anonymized users in Boston, Chicago and Miami.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of mobile food environments on fast food visits</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-09-22-you-are-where-you-eat-effect-of-mobile-food-environments-on-fast-food-visits/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-09-22-you-are-where-you-eat-effect-of-mobile-food-environments-on-fast-food-visits/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Bernardo Garcia-Bulle, Abigail L. Horn, Brooke M. Bell, Mohsen Bahrami, Burcin Bozkaya, Alex Pentland, Kayla de la Haye, and Esteban Moro
Publication: Nature Communications 15, article number: 2291. LINK
Abstract: Poor diets are a leading cause of morbidity and mortality. Exposure to low-quality food environments saturated with fast food outlets is hypothesized to negatively impact diet. However, food environment research has predominantly focused on static food environments around home neighborhoods and generated mixed findings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network constraints on worker mobility</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-01-16-network-constraints-on-worker-mobility/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2024-01-16-network-constraints-on-worker-mobility/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Morgan R. Frank, Esteban Moro, Tobin South, Alex Rutherford, Alex Pentland, Bledi Taska &amp;amp; Iyad Rahwan Publication: Nature Cities, 1, pages 94–104 (2024) LINK
Abstract: How do skills shape career mobility and access to cities’ labor markets? Here we model career pathways as an occupation network constructed from the similarity of occupations’ skill requirements within each US city. Using a nationally representative survey and three resume datasets, skill similarity predicts transition rates between occupations and predictions improve with increasingly granular skill data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The unequal effects of the health–economy trade-off during the COVID19 pandemic</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-11-20-the-unequal-effects-of-the-health-economy-trade-off-during-the-covid-19-pandemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-11-20-the-unequal-effects-of-the-health-economy-trade-off-during-the-covid-19-pandemic/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Marco Pangallo, Alberto Aleta, R. Maria del Rio-Chanona, Anton Pichler, David Martin-Corral, Matteo Chinazzi, Francois Lafond, Marco Ajelli, Esteban Moro, Yamir Moreno, Alessandro Vespignani, J. Doyne Farmer
Publication: Nature Human Behavior, Nov 16th, (2023)
LINK
Abstract: Despite the global impact of the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic, the question of whether mandated interventions have similar economic and public health effects as spontaneous behavioural change remains unresolved. Addressing this question, and understanding differential effects across socioeconomic groups, requires building quantitative and fine-grained mechanistic models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Population mobility data provides meaningful indicators of fast food intake and diet-related diseases in diverse populations</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-11-20-population-mobility-data-provides-meaningful-indicators-of-fast-food-intake-and-diet-related-diseases-in-diverse-populations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-11-20-population-mobility-data-provides-meaningful-indicators-of-fast-food-intake-and-diet-related-diseases-in-diverse-populations/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Abigail L. Horn, Brooke M. Bell, Bernardo Garcia Bulle Bueno, Mohsen Bahrami, Burcin Bozkaya, Yan Cui, John P. Wilson, Alex Pentland, Esteban Moro, Kayla de la Haye
Publication: NPJ Digital Medicine 6, 208 (2023)
LINK
Abstract: The characteristics of food environments people are exposed to, such as the density of fast food (FF) outlets, can impact their diet and risk for diet-related chronic disease. Previous studies examining the relationship between food environments and nutritional health have produced mixed findings, potentially due to the predominant focus on static food environments around people’s homes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phd Positions at SUN, NetSI, Northeastern University</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-10-20-phd-positions-at-sun-netsi-northeastern-university/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-10-20-phd-positions-at-sun-netsi-northeastern-university/</guid>
      <description>PhD Positions to work with my team at the Network Science Institute, Northeastern University
The Social Urban Networks (SUN) group, led by Dr. Esteban Moro, focuses on developing computational social science tools to address urban challenges, from climate change and inequality to health and economic development. By using large datasets of human behavior, tools and ideas from physics, applied mathematics, complex systems or network science, and collaborations with industry, government, and local communities, we seek not only to advance the understanding of the temporal dynamics of social systems to unprecedented levels but also to transform our findings into tools and policies to help achieve resilient and equitable adaptation of our societies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postdoc Positions at SUN, NetSI, Northeastern University</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-09-22-postdoc-positions-at-sun-netsi-northeastern/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-09-22-postdoc-positions-at-sun-netsi-northeastern/</guid>
      <description>Postdoc Positions to work with my team at the Network Science Institute, Northeastern University:
The Network Science Institute is seeking researchers at the postdoctoral and associate levels to join the new Social Urban Networks (SUN) group. The Social Urban Networks (SUN) group, led by Dr. Esteban Moro, focuses on developing computational social science tools to address urban challenges, from climate change and inequality to health and economic development. By using large datasets of human behavior, tools and ideas from physics, applied mathematics, complex systems or network science, and collaborations with industry, government, and local communities, we seek not only to advance the understanding of the temporal dynamics of social systems to unprecedented levels but also to transform our findings into tools and policies to help achieve resilient and equitable adaptation of our societies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Urban Networks at NetSI (Northeastern)</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-09-20-social-urban-networks-at-netsi-northeastern/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-09-20-social-urban-networks-at-netsi-northeastern/</guid>
      <description>I am thrilled to announce that I will be joining the Network Science Institute at Northeastern University as a Professor starting January 2024! As a researcher in Social Urban Networks (SUN) it is a dream come true.
My group will focus on developing computational social science tools to address urban challenges, from climate change, inequality to health and economic development. By using large datasets of human behavior, tools and ideas from physics, applied mathematics, complex systems or network science, and collaborations with industry, government, and local communities, we seek not only to advance the understanding of the temporal dynamics of social systems to unprecedented levels but also to transform our findings into tools and policies to help achieve resilient and equitable adaptation of our societies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long-Range Social Influence in Phone Communication Networks on Offline Adoption Decisions</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-06-21-long-range-social-influence-in-phone-communication-networks-on-offline-adoption-decisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-06-21-long-range-social-influence-in-phone-communication-networks-on-offline-adoption-decisions/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Yan Leng , Xiaowen Dong, Esteban Moro, Alex Pentland Publication: Information Systems Research, Articles in Advance 21 Jun (2023) LINK
Abstract: We use high-resolution mobile phone data with geolocation information and pro- pose a novel technical framework to study how social influence propagates within a phone communication network and affects the offline decision to attend a performance event. Our fine-grained data are based on the universe of phone calls made in a European country between January and July 2016.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying latent activity behaviors and lifestyles using mobility data to describe urban dynamics</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-11-28-identifying-latent-activity-behaviors-and-lifestyles-using-mobility-data-to-describe-urban-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-11-28-identifying-latent-activity-behaviors-and-lifestyles-using-mobility-data-to-describe-urban-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Yanni Yang, Alex Pentland, Esteban Moro Publication: EPJ Data Science 12, Article number: 15 (2023) LINK
Abstract: Urbanization and its problems require an in-depth and comprehensive understanding of urban dynamics, especially the complex and diversified lifestyles in modern cities. Digitally acquired data can accurately capture complex human activity, but it lacks the interpretability of demographic data. In this paper, we study a privacy-enhanced dataset of the mobility visitation patterns of 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral changes during the COVID-19 pandemic decreased income diversity of urban encounters</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-21-behavioral-changes-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-decreased-income-diversity-of-urban-encounters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-21-behavioral-changes-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-decreased-income-diversity-of-urban-encounters/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Takahiro Yabe, Bernardo García Bulle Bueno, Xiaowen Dong, Alex Pentland &amp;amp; Esteban Moro
Publication: Nature Communications volume 14, Article number: 2310 (2023) LINK
Abstract: Diversity of physical encounters in urban environments is known to spur economic productivity while also fostering social capital. However, mobility restrictions during the pandemic have forced people to reduce urban encounters, raising questions about the social implications of behavioral changes. In this paper, we study how individual income diversity of urban encounters changed during the pandemic, using a large-scale, privacy-enhanced mobility dataset of more than one million anonymized mobile phone users in Boston, Dallas, Los Angeles, and Seattle, across three years spanning before and during the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity beyond density: Experienced social mixing of urban streets</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-03-diversity-beyond-density-experienced-social-mixing-of-urban-streets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-03-diversity-beyond-density-experienced-social-mixing-of-urban-streets/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Zhuangyuan Fan, Tianyu Su, Maoran Sun, Ariel Noyman, Fan Zhang, Alex ‘Sandy’ Pentland, Esteban Moro
Publication: PNAS Nexus, Volumen 2, Issue 4, pgad077, 2023 LINK
Abstract: Urban density, in the form of residents’ and visitors’ concentration, is long considered to foster diverse exchanges of interpersonal knowledge and skills, which are intrinsic to sustainable human settlements. However, with current urban studies primarily devoted to city- and district-level analyses, we cannot unveil the elemental connection between urban density and diversity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A city is not a static tree: understanding urban areas through the lens of real-time behavioral data</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-02-24-a-city-is-not-a-static-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-02-24-a-city-is-not-a-static-tree/</guid>
      <description>Authors:Esteban Moro Publication: ZARCH, 19, 28–39. 2023 LINK
Abstract: Cities are the main ground on which our society and culture develop today and will evolve in the future. Against the traditional understanding of cities as physical spaces mostly around our neighborhoods, recent use of large-scale mobility datasets has enabled the study of our behavior at unprecedented spatial and temporal scales, much beyond our static residential spaces. Here we show how it is possible to use these datasets to investigate the role that human behavior plays in traditional urban problems like segregation, public health, or epidemics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Media Sensors to Detect Early Warnings of Influenza at Scale</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-11-18-social-media-sensors-to-detect-early-warnings-of-influenza-at-scale/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-11-18-social-media-sensors-to-detect-early-warnings-of-influenza-at-scale/</guid>
      <description>Authors: David Martín-Corral, Manuel García-Herranz, Manuel Cebrian, Esteban Moro Publication: medRxiv 2022.11.15.22282355 LINK
Abstract: Detecting early signs of an outbreak in a viral process is challenging due to its exponential nature, yet crucial given the benefits to public health it can provide. If available, the network structure where infection happens can provide rich information about the very early stages of viral outbreaks. For example, more central nodes have been used as social network sensors in biological or informational diffusion processes to detect early contagious outbreaks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral roots of inequality</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-behavioral-fundations-of-inequality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-behavioral-fundations-of-inequality/</guid>
      <description>Inequality is one of the most important problems in our societies. For example, economic inequality is today higher than it was in the 1970’s and by some metrics stands at levels not seen since the last Great Depression. A special form of segregation is that happening in our cities. We share the public places, our workplaces and our residential neighborhoods with people like us: same type of jobs, same education, similar economic status, and political opinions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral-network determinants of health outcomes.</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-10-25-behavioral-network-determinants-of-health-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-10-25-behavioral-network-determinants-of-health-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>Our behavior conditions our health. Exposure to infections depends on our and other people’s mobility. Exposure to healthy environments or habits depends on our choices and opportunities. Although human behavior is highly adaptive and dynamic, most social determinants of health are restricted to static aggregated representations of socio-demographic groups or residential environments.
We have started a program to understand behavioral-network determinants of health outcomes by modeling physical exposure between people and environments using large datasets of human mobility and activity and multilayer networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhythm of the streets: a street classification framework based on street activity patterns</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-07-29-rhythm-of-the-streets-a-street-classification-framework-based-on-street-activity-patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-07-29-rhythm-of-the-streets-a-street-classification-framework-based-on-street-activity-patterns/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Tianyu Su , Maoran Sun, Zhuangyuan Fan, Ariel Noyman, Alex Pentland, and Esteban Moro
Publication: EPJ Data Science 11, 43 (2022). Link
Abstract: As the living tissue connecting urban places, streets play significant roles in driving city development, providing essential access, and promoting human interactions. Understanding street activities and how these activities vary across different streets is critical for designing both efficient and livable streets. However, current street classification frameworks primarily focus on either streets’ functions in transportation networks or their adjacent land uses rather than actual activity patterns, resulting in coarse classifications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the importance and location of SARS-CoV-2 transmission events in large metropolitan areas</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-06-13-quantifying-the-importance-and-location-of-sars-cov-2-transmission-events-in-large-metropolitan-areas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-06-13-quantifying-the-importance-and-location-of-sars-cov-2-transmission-events-in-large-metropolitan-areas/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Alberto Aleta, David Martín-Corral, Michiel A.Bakker, Ana Pastore y Piontti, Marco Ajelli, Maria Litvinova , Matteo Chinazzi, Natalie E. Dean, M. Elizabeth Halloran,Ira M. Longini,Jr, Alex Pentland, Alessandro Vespignani, Yamir Moreno, and Esteban Moro. Publication: PNAS (2022). Link
Abstract: Detailed characterization of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) transmission across different settings can help design less disruptive interventions. We used real-time, privacy-enhanced mobility data in the New York City, NY and Seattle, WA metropolitan areas to build a detailed agent-based model of SARS-CoV-2infection to estimate the where, when, and magnitude of transmission events during thepandemic’s first wave.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wordle is getting (slightly) harder</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-02-14-wordle-is-getting-harder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-02-14-wordle-is-getting-harder/</guid>
      <description>Marty, I’ve been to the future and I have bad news. Wordle is getting harder. Not much, but harder.
 With millions of people playing the game Wordle online and the recent takeover by the New York times, some speculation about whether the game is getting harder is unavoidable. Since Wordle chooses a different word every day, some players have started to complain recent target words are harder to be guessed: It must be a coincidence, but the NY Times puzzles are hard and suddenly Wordle has questionable words</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generating synthetic mobility data for a realistic population with RNNs to improve utility and privacy</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-01-31-generating-synthetic-mobility-data-for-a-realistic-population-with-rnns-to-improve-utility-and-privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-01-31-generating-synthetic-mobility-data-for-a-realistic-population-with-rnns-to-improve-utility-and-privacy/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Alex Berke, Ronan Doorley, Kent Larson, Esteban Moro
Publication: arXiv preprint arXiv:2201.01139 (2022). Link
Abstract: Location data collected from mobile devices represent mobility behaviors at individual and societal levels. These data have important applications ranging from transportation planning to epidemic modeling. However, issues must be overcome to best serve these use cases: The data often represent a limited sample of the population and use of the data jeopardizes privacy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing (and winning) Wordle with R</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-01-10-wordle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-01-10-wordle/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Unless you have been away for the last month, you, your family or friends have been talking about or playing Wordle. It is a very straightforward game which reminds us (old enough) of the great MasterMind, but with words.
The idea is very simple. In the original version by Josh Wardle, we try to guess a (English) word of five letters. After each guess the game shows you what letters are in the answer in the right position (green), in the answer but in a wrong position (yellow) or not in the answer at all (gray).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating resilient urban labor economies</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-10-25-creating-resilient-urban-labor-economies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-10-25-creating-resilient-urban-labor-economies/</guid>
      <description>Like ecosystems, societies with adaptable economies are best prepared for the future. We started a research program to understand and detect economic resilience encoded in the dependency networks of agents, businesses, cities, or jobs. In particular, how much of the adaptability of our economies depends on the fragility of those economic networks? Can we identify weaknesses and design policies to strengthen those interdependent units?
Using highly detailed information about jobs, skills, and cities, our foundational study extended traditional economic models to show that the network structure of interactions and flows between jobs determines the resilience of labor markets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social networks as economic and social sensors</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-social-networks-as-sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-social-networks-as-sensors/</guid>
      <description>Temporal, structural and activity patterns in social networks are related to human behavior. Thus, networks do have different shape and dynamics under different exogenous and endogenous shocks or conditions. In the last years we have addressed the question of whether we can use our understanding of social networks to anticipate, predict or measure important phenomena as information propagation, disaster damage, unemployment shocks, weather conditions, gender digital divide, etc.
For example in a series of papers, we demonstrated for the first time the ability of the so-called &amp;ldquo;friendship paradox&amp;rdquo; in social networks to get better collection of users (sensors) that can anticipate meme, news or event-related information propagation in networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News or social media? Socio-economic divide of mobile service consumption</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-12-01-news-or-social-media-socio-economic-divide-of-mobile-service-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-12-01-news-or-social-media-socio-economic-divide-of-mobile-service-consumption/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Iñaki Ucar, Marco Gramaglia, Marco Fiore, Zbigniew Smoreda, and Esteban Moro Publication: J. R. Soc. Interface (2021). Link
Abstract: Reliable and timely information on socio-economic status and divides is critical to social and economic research and policing. Novel data sources from mobile communication platforms have enabled new cost-effective approaches and models to investigate social disparity, but their lack of interpretability, accuracy or scale has limited their relevance to date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobility patterns are associated with experienced income segregation in large US cities</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-07-31-mobility-patterns-are-associated-with-experienced-income-segregation-in-large-us-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-07-31-mobility-patterns-are-associated-with-experienced-income-segregation-in-large-us-cities/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro, Dan Calacci, Xiaowen Dong &amp;amp; Alex Pentland. Publication: Nature Communications 12, 4633 (2021). Link
Abstract: Traditional understanding of urban income segregation is largely based on static coarse grained residential patterns. However, these do not capture the income segregation experience implied by the rich social interactions that happen in places that may relate to individual choices, opportunities, and mobility behavior. Using a large-scale high-resolution mobility data set of 4.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of COVID-19 response policies on walking behavior in US cities</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-06-16-effect-of-covid-19-response-policies-on-walking-behavior-in-us-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-06-16-effect-of-covid-19-response-policies-on-walking-behavior-in-us-cities/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Ruth F. Hunter, Leandro Garcia, Thiago Herick de Sa, Belen Zapata-Diomedi, Christopher Millett, James Woodcock, Alex ’Sandy’ Pentland, and Esteban Moro Publication: Nature Communications (2021). Link
Abstract: The COVID-19 pandemic is causing mass disruption to our daily lives. We integrate mobility data from mobile devices and area-level data to study the walking patterns of 1.62 million anonymous users in 10 metropolitan areas in the United States. The data covers the period from mid-February 2020 (pre-lockdown) to late June 2020 (easing of lockdown restrictions).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Universal Resilience Patterns in labor markets</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-03-30-universal-resilience-patterns-in-labor-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-03-30-universal-resilience-patterns-in-labor-markets/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro, Morgan R. Frank, Alex Pentland, Alex Rutherford, Manuel Cebrian, Iyad Rahwan. Publication: Nature Communications (2021). Link
Abstract: Cities are the innovation centers of the US economy, but technological disruptions can exclude workers and inhibit a middle class. Therefore, urban policy must promote the jobs and skills that increase worker pay, create employment, and foster economic resilience. In this paper, we model labor market resilience with an ecologically-inspired job network constructed from the similarity of occupations’ skill requirements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factors Improving Labor Resiliency in U.S. Cities.</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-03-29-factors-improving-job-resiliency-in-u-s-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-03-29-factors-improving-job-resiliency-in-u-s-cities/</guid>
      <description>What makes urban labor markets more resilient? This is the question at the heart of a new study we have published in Nature Communications. We drew on prior network modeling research to map the job landscapes in cities across the United States, and showed that job “connectedness” is a key determinant of the resilience of local economies.
Economists, policy makers, city planners, and companies have a strong interest in determining what factors contribute to healthy job markets, including what factors can help promote faster recovery after a shock, such as a major recession or the current COVID pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the importance and location of SARS-CoV-2 transmission events in large metropolitan areas</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-12-09-effect-of-covid-19-response-policies-on-walking-behavior-in-us-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-12-09-effect-of-covid-19-response-policies-on-walking-behavior-in-us-cities/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Alberto Aleta, David Martin-Corral, Michiel Bakker, Ana Pastore y Piontti, Marco Ajelli, Maria Litvinova, Matteo Chinazzi, Natalie E Dean,M. Elizabeth Halloran, Ira M Longini, Alex Pentland, Alessandro Vespignani, Yamir Moreno, Esteban Moro
Publication: medRxiv (2020). Link
Abstract: Detailed characterizations of SARS-CoV-2 transmission risk across different social settings can inform the design of targeted and less disruptive non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPI), yet these data have been lacking. Here we integrate real-time, anonymous and privacy-enhanced geolocalized mobility data with census and demographic data in the New York City and Seattle metropolitan areas to build a detailed agent-based model of SARS-CoV-2 transmission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Art Map with R</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-10-19-personal-art-map-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-10-19-personal-art-map-with-r/</guid>
      <description>Map art makes beautiful posters. You can find them all over the internet and buy them even framed for your favorite city, area or country. Those posters&#39; beauty relies on the intricate and beautiful pattern of roads, buildings, parks, rivers, etc., which shape our cities and our mobility. In my research I constantly use those maps as the hardware fabric in which humans interact, move or encounter in urban settings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the impact of testing, contact tracing and household quarantine on second waves of COVID-19</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-09-18-modeling-the-impact-of-testing-contact-tracing-and-household-quarantine-on-second-waves-of-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-09-18-modeling-the-impact-of-testing-contact-tracing-and-household-quarantine-on-second-waves-of-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>Video of my talk &amp;ldquo;Modeling the impact of testing, contact tracing and household quarantine on second waves of COVID-19&amp;rdquo; at the Cycles of Seminars Covid-19 Sponsored by MexSAIM in UNAM, Mexico, September 15, 2020.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Segregated interactions in urban and online space</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-07-10-segregated-interactions-in-urban-and-online-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-07-10-segregated-interactions-in-urban-and-online-space/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Xiaowen Dong , Alfredo J. Morales, Eaman Jahani, Esteban Moro, Bruno Lepri, Burcin Bozkaya, Carlos Sarraute, Yaneer Bar-Yam and Alex Pentland Publication: EPJ Data Science 9, Article number: 20 LINK
Abstract: Urban income segregation is a widespread phenomenon that challenges societies across the globe. Classical studies on segregation have largely focused on the geographic distribution of residential neighborhoods rather than on patterns of social behaviors and interactions. In this study, we analyze segregation in economic and social interactions by observing credit card transactions and Twitter mentions among thousands of individuals in three culturally different metropolitan areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the impact of social distancing, testing, contact tracing and household quarantine on second-wave scenarios of the COVID-19 epidemic</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-05-27-modeling-the-impact-of-social-distancing-testing-contact-tracing-and-household-quarantine-on-second-wave-scenarios-of-the-covid-19-epidemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-05-27-modeling-the-impact-of-social-distancing-testing-contact-tracing-and-household-quarantine-on-second-wave-scenarios-of-the-covid-19-epidemic/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Alberto Aleta, David Martíın-Corral, Ana Pastore y Piontti, Marco Ajelli, Maria Litvinova, Matteo Chinazzi, Natalie E. Dean, M. Elizabeth Halloran, Ira M. Longini, Jr., Stefano Merler, Alex Pentland, Alessandro Vespignani, Esteban Moro &amp;amp; Yamir Moreno
Publication: Nature Human Behavior(2020). Link
Abstract: While severe social-distancing measures have proven effective in slowing the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, second-wave scenarios are likely to emerge as restrictions are lifted. Here we integrate anonymized, geolocalized mobility data with census and demographic data to build a detailed agent-based model of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) transmission in the Boston metropolitan area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Atlas of Inequality in US Cities</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-10-31-exploring-the-atlas-of-inequality-in-us-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-10-31-exploring-the-atlas-of-inequality-in-us-cities/</guid>
      <description>Video of my talk &amp;ldquo;Exploring the Atlas of Inequality in US Cities&amp;rdquo; at the Spatial Data Science Conference in University of Columbia (NY), October 2019
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Hide One&#39;s Relationships from Link Prediction Algorithms</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-10-22-how-to-hide-one-s-relationships-from-link-prediction-algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-10-22-how-to-hide-one-s-relationships-from-link-prediction-algorithms/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Marcin Waniek, Kai Zhou, Yevgeniy Vorobeychik, Esteban Moro, Tomasz P Michalak, Talal Rahwan
Journal: Scientific Reports volume 9, Article number: 12208 (2019) Link
Abstract: Our private connections can be exposed by link prediction algorithms. To date, this threat has only been addressed from the perspective of a central authority, completely neglecting the possibility that members of the social network can themselves mitigate such threats. We fill this gap by studying how an individual can rewire her own network neighborhood to hide her sensitive relationships.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>¿Cuánta gente vas a acabar conociendo en toda tu vida?</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-09-06-cua%CC%81nta-gente-vas-a-acabar-conociendo-en-toda-tu-vida/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-09-06-cua%CC%81nta-gente-vas-a-acabar-conociendo-en-toda-tu-vida/</guid>
      <description>Article (in Spanish) in the spanish newspaper El País about how many people we will know in our life. This is a summary of our recent research on how humans create/destroy relationships and how narrow and small is our world even throughout a life of encounters, relationships, work, etc.
¿Cuánta gente vas a acabar conociendo en toda tu vida? Muy poca
 En el mundo hay más de 7.500 millones de personas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019 Pictures</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-04-30-2019-pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-04-30-2019-pictures/</guid>
      <description>Some pictures of different activities during this year 2019
Talk at the Spatial Data Science Conference in Columbia, NY, October 2019. 450 participants, organized by Carto. Great conference!
Presenting our Atlas of Inequality tool at Imagination in Action, April 2019</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards understanding the impact of artificial intelligence on labor</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-26-towards-understanding-the-impact-of-artificial-intelligence-on-labor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-26-towards-understanding-the-impact-of-artificial-intelligence-on-labor/</guid>
      <description>title: &amp;lsquo;How to Organize your Deep Reinforcement Learning Agents: The Importance of Communication Topology&amp;rsquo; author: Esteban Moro date: &amp;lsquo;2018-12-14&amp;rsquo; categories:
 Publications tags: Deep Learning Networks image: /img/posts/NetES.jpg   Authors: Frank, Morgan R and Autor, David and Bessen, James E and Brynjolfsson, Erik and Cebrian, Manuel and Deming, David J and Feldman, Maryann and Groh, Matthew and Lobo, José and Moro, Esteban and Wang, Dashun and Youn, Hyejin and Rahwan, Iyad</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Atlas of Inequality</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-02-the-atlas-of-segregation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-02-the-atlas-of-segregation/</guid>
      <description>Segregation is hurting our societies and specially our cities. But economic inequality isn&amp;rsquo;t just limited to neighborhoods. The restaurants, stores, and other places we visit in cities are all unequal in their own way.
The Atlas of Inequality shows the income inequality of people who visit different places in the Boston metro area. It uses aggregated anonymous location data from digital devices to estimate people&amp;rsquo;s incomes and where they spend their time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up your blog with RStudio and blogdown II: Workflow</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-01-setting-up-your-blog-with-rstudio-and-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-01-setting-up-your-blog-with-rstudio-and-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>This is Part III of my series of posts about how to setup you blog with RStudio and blogdown. The other parts are:
   Part I about to setup the blog using Hugo, RStudio and blogdown Part II explains my workflow of creating new posts. Part III on how to modify the theme.   Workflow In Part I of this series of post we setup our new blog using blogdown and Hugo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up your blog with RStudio and blogdown III: modify your theme</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-04-setting-up-your-blog-with-rstudio-and-blogdown-iii-modify-your-theme/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-04-setting-up-your-blog-with-rstudio-and-blogdown-iii-modify-your-theme/</guid>
      <description>This is Part III of my series of posts about how to setup you blog with RStudio and blogdown. The other parts are:
   Part I about to setup the blog using Hugo, RStudio and blogdown Part II explains my workflow of creating new posts. Part III (this one) how to modify the theme.   In this post I am going to show how I modified the original theme casper-two that I use for my blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dynamic character of our networked society</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-the-dynamic-character-of-our-networked-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-the-dynamic-character-of-our-networked-society/</guid>
      <description>We live in a networked society and our actions, opinions, behaviors are affected and can affect other people. Understanding such social networked structures is one of the key challenges in our attempt to decode human behavior and its impact in our society. Although human interactions are dynamical by nature, most of our understanding relies in static representations of those social networks. However, social interactions are rarely static. Very often the networks evolve by means of processes that happen at diverse time scales, like link decay/formation, group formation, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Netmob 2019</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-01-netmob-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-01-netmob-2019/</guid>
      <description>Another edition of Netmob is happening this year 2019. NetMob is the primary conference in the analysis of mobile phone datasets in social, urban, societal and industrial problems. Previous editions in Boston and Milano brought together more than 250 researchers, practitioners and decision-makers from more 140 institutions and 30 countries. I had the pleasure to organize the 2015 edition and it was a blast to put together so much interesting talks, people, projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up our blog with RStudio and blogdown I: Creating the blog</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-setting-up-your-blog-with-rstudio-and-blogdown-i-creating-the-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-setting-up-your-blog-with-rstudio-and-blogdown-i-creating-the-blog/</guid>
      <description>Last month I migrated my blog from Wordpress to Hugo and blogdown. Now I can post from RStudio using R/markdown, which allow me to create interactive posts including R code. It has been such a good experience that I decide to write down how to do it with three posts to help others.
 This one about to setup the blog. Part II explains my workflow of creating new posts. and Part III on how to modify the theme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 pictures</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-21-2018-pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-21-2018-pictures/</guid>
      <description>Some pictures of different activities during this year 2018
A group of us from Scallable Cooperation group at MediaLab visited Riyad, Abu Dhabi and Dubai to talk about Future of Work.
Complenet happenned in Boston this year. Here I am talking about how do you met your best friend?
I was an invited speaker at NERCCS 2018 conference to talk about our work on the dynamics of strong ties
A bunch of network scientist close to the Netsci 2018 venue</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Growing old in Twitter</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-14-growing-old-in-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-14-growing-old-in-twitter/</guid>
      <description>I started using Twitter more than 10 years ago (!). I open an account in this social network in 2008 and although I was not using it too much for the first year, I become a frequent user after that. It has helped me to get news, information both for my personal and professional interests. But not only that, Twitter has been also the data source for our research, that helped us to investigate the relationship between human behavior in the social platform and paramount problems in our society as information propagation, unemployment, disaster damage, political opinion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Organize your Deep Reinforcement Learning Agents: The Importance of Communication Topology</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-14-how-to-organize-your-deep-reinforcement-learning-agents-the-importance-of-communication-topology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-14-how-to-organize-your-deep-reinforcement-learning-agents-the-importance-of-communication-topology/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Dhaval Adjodah, Dan Calacci, Abhimanyu Dubey, Peter Krafft, Esteban Moro, Alex `Sandy&#39; Pentland
Journal: Preprint (2018). arXiv
Abstract: In this empirical paper, we investigate how learning agents can be arranged in more efficient communication topologies for improved learning. This is an important problem because a common technique to improve speed and robustness of learning in deep reinforcement learning and many other machine learning algorithms is to run multiple learning agents in parallel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La burbuja política o cómo las redes multiplican la colisión entre quienes piensan distinto</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-12-la-burbuja-poli%CC%81tica-o-co%CC%81mo-las-redes-multiplican-la-colisio%CC%81n-entre-quienes-piensan-distinto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-12-12-la-burbuja-poli%CC%81tica-o-co%CC%81mo-las-redes-multiplican-la-colisio%CC%81n-entre-quienes-piensan-distinto/</guid>
      <description>Article in the spanish newspaper La Vanguardia about how social media is increasing polarization and radicalization in political opinion. With a quote to my opinion on this.
La burbuja política o cómo las redes multiplican la colisión entre quienes piensan distinto
 Para Esteban Moro, investigador del Instituto de Tecnología de Massachusetts (MIT) y de la Universidad Carlos III, este trabajo “confirma lo que ya sabíamos acerca del efecto de partidismo o cámaras de eco.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ScamCoins, S*** Posters, and the Search for the Next Bitcoin(TM): Collective Sensemaking in Cryptocurrency Discussions</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-11-07-scamcoins-s-posters-and-the-search-for-the-next-bitcointm-collective-sensemaking-in-cryptocurrency-discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 14:41:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-11-07-scamcoins-s-posters-and-the-search-for-the-next-bitcointm-collective-sensemaking-in-cryptocurrency-discussions/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Eaman Jahani, Peter M. Krafft, Yoshihiko Suhara, Esteban Moro, Alex “Sandy” Pentland
Journal: Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 2, CSCW, Article 79 (November 2018), 28 pages. LINK
Abstract: Participants in cryptocurrency markets are in constant communication with each other about the latest coins and news releases. Do these conversations build hype through the contagiousness of excitement, help the community process information, or play some other role? Using a novel dataset from a major cryptocurrency forum, we conduct an exploratory study of the characteristics of online discussion around cryptocurrencies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing gender inequality through large-scale Facebook advertising data</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-06-19-analyzing-gender-inequality-through-large-scale-facebook-advertising-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2018 21:34:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-06-19-analyzing-gender-inequality-through-large-scale-facebook-advertising-data/</guid>
      <description>Authors: David Garcia, Yonas Mitike Kassa, Angel Cuevas, Manuel Cebrian, Esteban Moro, Iyad Rahwan, and Ruben Cuevas
Journal: PNAS June 19, 2018. 201717781. LINK
Abstract: Online social media are information resources that can have a transformative power in society. While the Web was envisioned as an equalizing force that allows everyone to access information, the digital divide prevents large amounts of people from being present online. Online social media, in particular, are prone to gen- der inequality, an important issue given the link between social media use and employment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weather impacts expressed sentiment</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-04-28-weather-impacts-expressed-sentiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 08:56:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-04-28-weather-impacts-expressed-sentiment/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Patrick Baylis, Nick Obradovich, Yury Kryvasheyeu, Haohui Chen, Lorenzo Coviello, Esteban Moro, Manuel Cebrian, James H. Fowler
Journal: PLoS ONE 13(4): e0195750 (2018) LINK
Abstract: We conduct the largest ever investigation into the relationship between meteorological con- ditions and the sentiment of human expressions. To do this, we employ over three and a half billion social media posts from tens of millions of individuals from both Facebook and Twitter between 2009 and 2016.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MemeSequencer: Sparse Matching for Embedding Image Macros</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-04-24-memesequencer-sparse-matching-for-embedding-image-macros/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 11:20:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2018-04-24-memesequencer-sparse-matching-for-embedding-image-macros/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Abhimanyu Dubey, Esteban Moro, Manuel Cebrian, Iyad Rahwan
Journal: WWW&#39;18 Proceedings of the Web Conference 2018 LINK
Abstract: The analysis of the creation, mutation, and propagation of social media content on the Internet is an essential problem in computational social science, affecting areas ranging from marketing to political mobilization. A first step towards understanding the evolution of images online is the analysis of rapidly modifying and propagating memetic imagery or ‘memes’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Media Lab, el lugar donde se inventa el futuro</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-media-lab-el-lugar-donde-se-inventa-el-futuro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-media-lab-el-lugar-donde-se-inventa-el-futuro/</guid>
      <description>Report in Magazine (in Spanish) about the work done by different groups at the MIT MediaLab, including ours!
Media Lab, el lugar donde se inventa el futuro
 “Aquí no se busca un éxito incremental en los proyectos, como sucede en muchas universidades, ni tampoco desarrollos a largo plazo, sino que tratan de dar con moonshots, es decir, aspectos que a largo plazo pueden impactar en la sociedad. No hay departamentos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La era del algoritmo ha llegado y tus datos son un tesoro</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-la-era-del-algoritmo-ha-llegado-y-tus-datos-son-un-tesoro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-la-era-del-algoritmo-ha-llegado-y-tus-datos-son-un-tesoro/</guid>
      <description>Article in El País (in Spanish) about how algorithms are now the big asset of companies, agencies and researchers to transform data into value
La era del algoritmo ha llegado y tus datos son un tesoro
 “La primera revolución llegó hace unos años con el almacenamiento de inmensas cantidades de datos procedentes de las huellas electrónicas que todos dejamos. La segunda, en la que estamos inmersos, procede de la capacidad que tanto empresarios como usuarios o investigadores tienen para analizar estos datos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soluciones para ciudades grandes y pequeñas ante la automatización de empleos</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-soluciones-para-ciudades-grandes-y-pequen%CC%83as-ante-la-automatizacio%CC%81n-de-empleos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-soluciones-para-ciudades-grandes-y-pequen%CC%83as-ante-la-automatizacio%CC%81n-de-empleos/</guid>
      <description>Article (in Spanish) in MIT Technology Review (and the Sacyr innovation blog) about how automation is going to impact differently big or small cities.
Soluciones para ciudades grandes y pequeñas ante la automatización de empleos
 La razón principal para que la automatización ataque más a los núcleos pequeños se debe a la propia naturaleza de los empleos disponibles en cada tipo de urbe. Las ciudades más pequeñas tienen más profesiones rutinarias y repetitivas, &amp;ldquo;como las tareas de servicios, labores mecánicas, fábricas y agricultura, que son susceptibles de ser automatizadas&amp;rdquo;, apunta el investigador del Media Lab y profesor de la Universidad Carlos III de Madrid Esteban Moro.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Important relationships are not bursty</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2017/12/important-relationships-are-not-bursty/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 15:32:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2017/12/important-relationships-are-not-bursty/</guid>
      <description>What are the properties of a long-lasting relationship? This important question as intrigued the social scientists during the last decades and has triggered numerous publications, surveys and experiments to detect what patterns are behind social relationships that persist. Probably the most famous finding is that of Granovetter who proposed that strong relationships are the ones more likely to persist in the future. And what is a strong relationship? According to Granovetter, a strong relationship is that with high intensity (a lot of interactions), intimacy (mutual confiding) and large structural redundancy (lots of common friends).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Participation in “El cazador de cerebros” by RTVE</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-participation-in-el-cazador-de-cerebros-by-rtve/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-participation-in-el-cazador-de-cerebros-by-rtve/</guid>
      <description>This episode of the Spanish television program El Cazador de cerebros show the uses of Big Data in social problems. Shot at MIT Medialab, I share the episode with friends like Manuel García Herranz (who works and shows much cooler things that I do.)
El Cazador de Cerebros</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk at NICO &#34;The lifetime of strong ties in social networks&#34;</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-the-lifetime-of-strong-ties-in-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-the-lifetime-of-strong-ties-in-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>Video of my talk &amp;ldquo;The lifetime of strong ties in social networks&amp;rdquo; at the Northwestern Institute of Complex Systems (NICO) in Evaston, Chicago, Oct 2017. What a great experience giving a talk at NICO!
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal patterns behind the strength of persistent ties</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2017-06-28-temporal-patterns-behind-the-strength-of-persistent-ties/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 12:54:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2017-06-28-temporal-patterns-behind-the-strength-of-persistent-ties/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Henry Navarro, Giovanna Miritello, Arturo Canales, Esteban Moro
Journal: EPJ Data Science (2017) 6:31 LINK
Abstract: Social networks are made out of strong and weak ties having very different structural and dynamical properties. But what features of human interaction build a strong tie? Here we approach this question from a practical way by finding what are the properties of social interactions that make ties more persistent and thus stronger to maintain social interactions in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Science for kids!</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2017/03/network-science-for-kids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 13:58:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2017/03/network-science-for-kids/</guid>
      <description>One of my favorite activities is to teach my field or research (network science) to high-schoolers. We (together with my colleague Cristina Brändle) have been doing that from our university to the local high schools in Madrid. Since they know concepts like equations, probability or geometry, it is somehow easy to show them concepts like what is a network, small world, friendship paradox or centrality. We usually have transparencies and allow them to work on Excel to perform some calculations which works well to understand the basic concepts of networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter Session Analytics: Profiling Users’ Short-Term Behavioral Changes</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2017-03-07-twitter-session-analytics-profiling-users-short-term-behavioral-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 14:25:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2017-03-07-twitter-session-analytics-profiling-users-short-term-behavioral-changes/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Farshad Kooti, Esteban Moro, and Kristina Lerman
Journal: Proceedings of SocInfo 2016 LINK
Abstract: Human behavior shows strong daily, weekly, and monthly patterns. In this work, we demonstrate online behavioral changes that occur on a much smaller time scale: minutes, rather than days or weeks. Specifically, we study how people distribute their effort over different tasks during periods of activity on the Twitter social platform. We demonstrate that later in a session on Twitter, people prefer to per- form simpler tasks, such as replying and retweeting others’ posts, rather than composing original messages, and they also tend to post shorter messages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>El romance entre Twitter y la ciencia</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2017-01-30-el-romance-entre-twitter-y-la-ciencia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2017-01-30-el-romance-entre-twitter-y-la-ciencia/</guid>
      <description>Nice article (in Spanish) in Yorokobu magazine about the use of Twitter in science, highlighting our work on the use of social media for rapid assessment of natural disaster management
El romance entre Twitter y la ciencia
 «Twitter y las otras redes sociales están entre los más grandes archivos de actividad humana existentes y, al contrario que con las encuestas, ahora tenemos la posibilidad de analizar millones de mensajes, opiniones e interacciones de personas en diferentes contextos como la política, economía o el ocio», explica el matemático Esteban Moro, investigador en la Carlos III de Madrid.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Financial markets as empirical labs to study the evolving ecology of human decision making</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-financial-markets-as-empirical-labs-to-study-the-evolving-ecology-of-human-decision-making/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-financial-markets-as-empirical-labs-to-study-the-evolving-ecology-of-human-decision-making/</guid>
      <description>Human decision making strategies evolve through time based on past experience and they are influence by the spectrum of other strategies with which they come into contact. Financial markets provide the best empirical lab to understand how human decide under risk and uncertainty. They are complex systems which provide massive datasets of detail records of human decisions which constantly evolve and collide in centralized or social structures. Furthermore financial markets provide us with a very simple measure of performance (profits, ROI), thus enabling us to study the relationship between human decision making strategies and performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016 pictures</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-12-20-2016-pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-12-20-2016-pictures/</guid>
      <description>Some pictures of different activities during this year 2016
I was invited to give a tutorial about temporal networs at the Workshop on Complex Network Mining and Analysis in Workclaw. Here we are hanging out with some of the other speakers (Bruno Goncalves and Marton Karsai)
Just arrived to Boston, I gave a talk at Netsi about our work on Temporal Networks at Netsci, Northeastern University.
Working at the Medialab I got the opportunity to talk about our work in other groups, like Scalable Cooperation here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Big Data&#34;: La nueva materia prima</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2016/06/big-data-la-nueva-materia-prima/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 07:52:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2016/06/big-data-la-nueva-materia-prima/</guid>
      <description>Article in El País (in spanish) about the recent one day workshop on the public-private partnerships to exploit the power of big data in our society. Organized by El País, Vodafone Institute and DataPopAlliance.
Here is the online version: http://economia.elpais.com/economia/2016/06/03/actualidad/1464954943_672966.html </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fully nonlinear dynamics of stochastic thin-film dewetting</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-12-28-fully-nonlinear-dynamics-of-stochastic-thin-film-dewetting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2016 09:06:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-12-28-fully-nonlinear-dynamics-of-stochastic-thin-film-dewetting/</guid>
      <description>Authors: S. Nesic, R. Cuerno, E. Moro, and L. Kondic
Journal: Physical Review E 92, 061002(R) LINK | PDF
Abstract: The spontaneous formation of droplets via dewetting of a thin fluid film from a solid substrate allows materials nanostructuring. Often, it is crucial to be able to control the evolution, and to produce patterns characterized by regularly spaced droplets. While thermal fluctuations are expected to play a role in the dewetting process, their relevance has remained poorly understood, particularly during the nonlinear stages of evolution that involve droplet formation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid assessment of disaster damage using social media activity</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-03-14-rapid-assessment-of-disaster-damage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2016 09:06:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-03-14-rapid-assessment-of-disaster-damage/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Yury Kryvasheyeu1, Haohui Chen, Nick Obradovich, Esteban Moro, Pascal Van Hentenryck, James Fowler and Manuel Cebrian
Journal: Science Advances 11 Mar 2016: Vol. 2, no. 3, e1500779 (2016) LINK
Abstract: Could social media data aid in disaster response and damage assessment? Countries face both an increasing frequency and an increasing intensity of natural disasters resulting from climate change. During such events, citizens turn to social media platforms for disaster-related communication and information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Searching for someone</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-02-19-searching-for-someone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 11:52:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-02-19-searching-for-someone/</guid>
      <description>From the “Small World Experiment” to the “Red Balloon Challenge,” and beyond
We live in a small world, right? But the cost and fragility of navigating it could harm any potential strategy to leverage the power of social networks. Read this fascinating story of the research, experiments, and failures in the quest for using social networks to search information/people:
[Excerpt of the article] Our ability to search social networks for people and information is fundamental to our success.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview in &#34;El Mundo&#34; newspaper</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2016/02/interview-in-el-mundo-newspaper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 09:31:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2016/02/interview-in-el-mundo-newspaper/</guid>
      <description>El Mundo &amp;ldquo;Papel&amp;rdquo; Magazine published an interview with me about the uses (and abuses) of big data in research/industry. The headline is a little bit controversial, but I talk about many other things like the use of BigData in development, administrations, health and politics.
Here is the link
And the printer version is here: </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More people, more fun: The scaling of events in cities</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2016/02/more-people-more-fun-the-scaling-of-events-in-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 09:25:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2016/02/more-people-more-fun-the-scaling-of-events-in-cities/</guid>
      <description>This is a recent article publish in Medium.com by David Martín-Corral, Manuel Cebrián and myself in which we analyze the super-scaling of touristic attraction (number of events) with population. Amazingly we found that the number of events (music/theater/sports/etc.) scales super-linearly with the population of the city.
So yes! more people means more fun!
Read the article in Medium</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;Dynamics in Complex Networks: Analysing Real-world Data&#34;</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-01-07-talk-dynamics-in-complex-networks-analysing-real-world-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2016-01-07-talk-dynamics-in-complex-networks-analysing-real-world-data/</guid>
      <description>Video of my talk &amp;ldquo;Dynamics in Complex Networks: Analysing Real-world Data&amp;rdquo; at the Workshop on Complex Network Mining and Analysis in Wrocław, Poland, January 2016
 You can also find the transparencies here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 year in review</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2015/12/2015-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 22:05:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2015/12/2015-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>2015 has been an amazing year both on the professional and personal grounds. Here are some of the main things that happened this year:
 I helped to build up the &amp;ldquo;Master in Data Science and Big Data in Finance&amp;rdquo; at the Afi School of Finance. In this first edition we had 18 incredible students and the support from most of the big financial companies in Spain and the best researchers, practitioners and data scientist in the financial industry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2015 Pictures</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2015/12/2015-pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 23:17:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2015/12/2015-pictures/</guid>
      <description>Some pictures of different activities during this year 2015
Giving a talk at Espacio Fundación Telefónica http://espacio.fundaciontelefonica.com/2015/03/03/big-bang-data-big-data-una-mirada-global/
Group of speakers at databeers with our t-shirt cellebrating one year of talks at databeers madrid
Room full packed at Databeers Madrid
Talking about data and development at UPM
In November 2015 I had the opportunity to talk about social networks and relationships at Google Campus. Invited by the great team of Graphext (here with Victoriano Izquierdo)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal networks with R and igraph (updated)</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-12-21-temporal-networks-with-r-and-igraph-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 21:17:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-12-21-temporal-networks-with-r-and-igraph-updated/</guid>
      <description>A while ago, I wrote a post about how to create animations of temporal networks using R and the amazing package igraph package. The post was written in 2012 and the code does not work with the most recent versions (1.0) of igraph. Here I revisited that post, improving its performance and also making it consistent with the new versions of the package and R.
First of all, let me remind you the basic idea: we want to get an animated evolution of a network in which nodes/edges appear (and/or disappear) dynamically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Video of my talk “Your data, our society&#34;</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-video-of-my-talk-your-data-our-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-01-01-video-of-my-talk-your-data-our-society/</guid>
      <description>Video of my talk &amp;ldquo;your data, our society&amp;rdquo; given at #sngular810, the S|ngular presentation event celebrated in Madrid in Oct. 2015. In my talk I show the uses of bigdata at different scales of resolution to understand our society.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daily rhythms in mobile telephone communication</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-10-13-daily-rhythms-in-mobile-telephone-communication/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 13:23:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-10-13-daily-rhythms-in-mobile-telephone-communication/</guid>
      <description>Authors:Talayeh Aledavood , Eduardo López, Sam G. B. Roberts, Felix Reed-Tsochas, Esteban Moro, Robin I. M. Dunbar, Jari Saramäki
Journal: PLoS ONE 10(9), e0138098 (2015) LINK
Abstract: Circadian rhythms are known to be important drivers of human activity and the recent availability of electronic records of human behaviour has provided fine-grained data of temporal patterns of activity on a large scale. Further, questionnaire studies have identified important individual differences in circadian rhythms, with people broadly categorised into morning-like or evening-like individuals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk at itdUPM2015 &#34;Nowcasting. Sociedades para nuevas formas de organización&#34;</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-09-24-talk-at-itdupm2015-nowcasting-sociedades-para-nuevas-formas-de-organizacio%CC%81n/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-09-24-talk-at-itdupm2015-nowcasting-sociedades-para-nuevas-formas-de-organizacio%CC%81n/</guid>
      <description>Video of my talk &amp;ldquo;Nowcasting. Sociedades para nuevas formas de organización&amp;rdquo; in the conference &amp;ldquo;Tecnología e Innovación para el Desarrollo&amp;rdquo; at Universidad Politécnica de Madrid.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Seconds to Months: multi-scale dynamics of mobile telephone calls</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-05-07-from-seconds-to-months-multi-scale-dynamics-of-mobile-telephone-calls/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 12:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-05-07-from-seconds-to-months-multi-scale-dynamics-of-mobile-telephone-calls/</guid>
      <description>Authors:Jari Saramaki, Esteban Moro
Journal: Eur. Phys. J. B (2015) 88: 164 LINK | **arXiv
Abstract: Big Data on electronic records of social interactions allow approaching human behaviour and sociality from a quantitative point of view with unforeseen statistical power. Mobile telephone Call Detail Records (CDRs), automatically collected by telecom operators for billing purposes, have proven especially fruitful for understanding one-to-one communication patterns as well as the dynamics of social networks that are reflected in such patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social media fingerprints of unemployment</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-11-13-social-media-fingerprints-of-unemployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 12:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-11-13-social-media-fingerprints-of-unemployment/</guid>
      <description>Authors:Alejandro Llorente, Manuel García-Herránz, Manuel Cebrián and Esteban Moro
Journal: PLoS ONE 10(5): e0128692 (2014) LINK
Summary: Publicly available social media data can be used to quantify deviations from typical patterns of behavior and uncover how these deviations signal the socio-economical status of regions. Using data from geolocalized Twitter messages, we find that unemployment is correlated with technology adoption, daily activity, diversity in mobility patterns and correctness in communication style. These behavioral metrics serve to build simple, interpretable, and cost-effective socio-economical predictors from these novel digital datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Netmob 2015</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-04-14-netmob-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 09:26:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2015-04-14-netmob-2015/</guid>
      <description>I had the pleasure to organize last edition of Netmob at MIT Media Lab (together with Sandy Pentland, Vincent Blondel and Yves-Alexandre de Montjoye). Netmob is the primary conference in the analysis of those datasets in social, urban, societal and industrial problems. Netmob 2015 also hosted the final part of theD4D Challenge by Orange. They were 3 amazing days of applications and analysis of mobile phone datasets, preceded by one-day school and 3 days Hackathon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2014 Pictures</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2015/01/2014-pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2015 15:10:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2015/01/2014-pictures/</guid>
      <description>Some pictures about different things that happen in 2014
Sobre los rumores que se propagan en Twitter a raíz de lo que pasó en Canarias con el supuesto avión amerizado
Jornada 25 Aniversario del Instituto de Ingeniería del COnocimiento, Madrid, 11 Junio de 2014</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic Response to Microscopic Intrinsic Noise in Three-Dimensional Fisher Fronts</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-11-03-macroscopic-response-to-microscopic-intrinsic-noise-in-three-dimensional-fisher-fronts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 08:22:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-11-03-macroscopic-response-to-microscopic-intrinsic-noise-in-three-dimensional-fisher-fronts/</guid>
      <description>Authors:Svetozar Nesic, Rodolfo Cuerno, and Esteban Moro
Journal: Physical Review Letters 113, 180602 (2014) LINK
Summary We study the dynamics of three-dimensional Fisher fronts in the presence of density fluctuations. To this end we simulate the Fisher equation subject to stochastic internal noise, and study how the front moves and roughens as a function of the number of particles in the system, N. Our results suggest that the macroscopic behaviour of the system is driven by the microscopic dynamics at its leading edge where number fluctuations are dominated by rare events.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sistemas para predecir las tendencias de las redes sociales</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/05/sistemas-para-predecir-las-tendencias-de-las-redes-sociales/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2014 20:35:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/05/sistemas-para-predecir-las-tendencias-de-las-redes-sociales/</guid>
      <description>Entrevista en el programa &amp;ldquo;La noche en Vela&amp;rdquo; de Radio Nacional de España sobre nuestro estudio de sensores en las redes sociales
[iframe frameborder=&amp;ldquo;0&amp;rdquo; src=&amp;ldquo;http://www.rtve.es/drmn/embed/audio/2562847&amp;rdquo; name=&amp;ldquo;Sistemas para predecir las tendencias de las redes sociales&amp;rdquo; scrolling=&amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; style=&amp;ldquo;width:100%;height:150px;left:0;top:0;overflow:hidden;&amp;rdquo; ]
Sistemas para predecir las tendencias de las redes sociales</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>El método que identifica la información que será relevante en las redes sociales</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/05/el-metodo-que-identifica-la-informacion-que-sera-relevante-en-las-redes-sociales/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 21:35:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/05/el-metodo-que-identifica-la-informacion-que-sera-relevante-en-las-redes-sociales/</guid>
      <description>Interview in the COPE radio station about our work on using friends as sensors to detect global information outbreaks 
[iframe src=&amp;ldquo;http://vod.cope.es/audio/2014/05/02/audio_13989914248167823110.mp3&amp;rdquo; width=&amp;ldquo;425&amp;rdquo; height=&amp;ldquo;65&amp;rdquo; frameborder=&amp;ldquo;0&amp;rdquo; scrolling=&amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comunidades de partidarios en redes sociales: estudio de las elecciones catalanas de 2010 y 2012</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-04-22-comunidades-de-partidarios-en-redes-sociales-estudio-de-las-elecciones-catalanas-de-2010-y-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 12:48:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-04-22-comunidades-de-partidarios-en-redes-sociales-estudio-de-las-elecciones-catalanas-de-2010-y-2012/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro
Book: Cotarelo, R. &amp;amp; Olmeda, J.A. (Comps.) (forthcoming). La democracia del siglo XXI. Política, medios de comunicación, internet y redes sociales. Actas de las II Jornadas españolas de ciberpolítica, 28 de mayo de 2013. Madrid: Centro de Estudios Políticos y Constitucionales. [pdf]
Abstract: En los últimos años hemos asistido a un incremento notable de eventos de carácter político y/o social que han sido promovidos (cuando no originados) a través de medios de comunicación electrónicos.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Following information in social networks: how social structure and dynamics impact message transmission</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/04/following-information-in-social-networks-how-social-structure-and-dynamics-impact-message-transmission/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 10:03:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/04/following-information-in-social-networks-how-social-structure-and-dynamics-impact-message-transmission/</guid>
      <description>Talk about our research on spreading in social networks at Jornadas MAVIR
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Friends as Sensors to Detect Global-Scale Contagious Outbreaks</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-04-09-using-friends-as-sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 13:37:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-04-09-using-friends-as-sensors/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Manuel Garcia-Herranz, Esteban Moro, Manuel Cebrian, Nicholas A. Christakis and James H. Fowler
Journal: PLoS ONE 9(4): e92413 (2014) LINK
SummaryRecent research has focused on the monitoring of global–scale online data for improved detection of epidemics, mood patterns, movements in the stock market political revolutions, box-office revenues, consumer behaviour and many other important phenomena. However, privacy considerations and the sheer scale of data available online are quickly making global monitoring infeasible, and existing methods do not take full advantage of local network structure to identify key nodes for monitoring.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk in &#34;Mathematics of Social Learning&#34;</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/02/talk-in-mathematics-of-social-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2014 09:18:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/02/talk-in-mathematics-of-social-learning/</guid>
      <description>I was recently invited to give a talk in the workshop entitled &amp;ldquo;Mathematics of Social Learning&amp;rdquo; which took place at the Institute of Pure and Applied Mathematics in UCLA, Los Angeles. Here is the program in which you can also find the recorded videos of the talks.
May talk entitled &amp;ldquo;Are you a social keeper or a social explorer&amp;rdquo; about our research on communication strategies was recorded too. Enjoy!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Performance of Social Network Sensors During Hurricane Sandy</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-02-13-performance-of-social-network-sensors-during-hurricane-sandy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 13:57:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2014-02-13-performance-of-social-network-sensors-during-hurricane-sandy/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Yury Kryvasheyeu, Haohui Chen, Esteban Moro, Pascal Van Hentenryck, Manuel Cebrian Journal: PLoS ONE 10(2): e0117288 (2015) LINK
Summary Information flow during catastrophic events is a critical aspect of disaster management. Modern communication platforms, in particular online social networks, provide an opportunity to study such flow, and a mean to derive early-warning sensors, improving emergency preparedness and response. Performance of the social networks sensor method, based on topological and behavioural properties derived from the &amp;ldquo;friendship paradox&amp;rdquo;, is studied here for over 50 million Twitter messages posted before, during, and after Hurricane Sandy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entrevista sobre Big Data Geo-referenciado</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/entrevista-sobre-big-data-geo-referenciado/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 17:18:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/entrevista-sobre-big-data-geo-referenciado/</guid>
      <description>En Open-buzz.com: sobre los datos georeferenciados.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Las matemáticas de la amistad: redes sociales</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/las-matematicas-de-la-amistad-redes-sociales/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 23:51:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/las-matematicas-de-la-amistad-redes-sociales/</guid>
      <description>[In Spanish] Entrevista en el programa Eureka de Radio Nacional sobre las matemáticas de las redes sociales
Eureka - Las matemáticas de la amistad: redes sociales - 15/11/13Escuchar audio
 * [**Eureka - Las matemáticas de la amistad: redes sociales - 15/11/13**](http://192.168.249.98/alacarta/audios/eureka/eureka-matematicas-amistad-redes-sociales-15-11-13/2144176.shtml)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>¿Qué hay detrás de los vídeos más vistos en Internet?</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/que-hay-detras-de-los-videos-mas-vistos-en-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 23:20:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/que-hay-detras-de-los-videos-mas-vistos-en-internet/</guid>
      <description>[In Spanish] Reportaje en los informativos de Antena 3 sobre por qué algunos vídeos se propagan de manera viral y otros no.
Más vídeos en Antena3</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 pictures</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/2013-pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 22:48:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/2013-pictures/</guid>
      <description>Some pictures about different things that happen in 2013
Receiving the 2013 award of research excellence from the President of our University
Nice picture with Alejandro Llorente and Marcelo Soria. Waiting to talk at Barcelona Media
Given one (of the 3) talks at NetSci&#39;13 in Copenhaguen
Presenting our work about the &amp;ldquo;Limits of social mobilization&amp;rdquo; in Barcelona Media
Presenting Giovanna&amp;rsquo;s PhD thesis (published in Springer) at Telefonica I+D Boecillo (Valladolid)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best papers of the 2013. What is privacy? </title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/best-papers-of-the-2013-what-is-privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 12:40:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2014/01/best-papers-of-the-2013-what-is-privacy/</guid>
      <description>I have read around 200 papers this year. A large fraction of them were very technical, some reviews and other very fashionable. But among them, I would like to highlight the ones that for me are the best. This is a personal selection and it is based not only on the technical aspects, but more on their impact. Specifically, these two papers change the way we look at privacy and how our actions reveal important information about us which was not obvious in the first place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Via Catalana from the Twittersphere</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2013/11/via-catalana-from-the-twittersphere/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2013 10:10:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2013/11/via-catalana-from-the-twittersphere/</guid>
      <description>Joint work by
 Manuel García-Herranz, Department of Computer Science, Universidad Autonóma de Madrid Manuel Cebrián, National Information and Communications Technology Australia, University of Melbourne Esteban Moro, Department of Mathematics, Universidad Carlos III de Madrid  While public demonstrations are Social Science’s most important and studied phenomena, they are also the most mysterious and poorly understood ones. Demonstrations trigger new social movements, change countries attitudes, and have the potential to overthrow governments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time allocation in social networks: correlation between social structure and human communication dynamics</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-05-17-time-allocation-in-social-networks-correlation-between-social-structure-and-human-communication-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 07:47:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-05-17-time-allocation-in-social-networks-correlation-between-social-structure-and-human-communication-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Giovanna Miritello, Rubén Lara, and Esteban Moro
Book: &amp;ldquo;Temporal Networks&amp;rdquo;, Springer, 2013. Series: Understanding Complex Systems. Holme, Petter; Saramaki, Jari (Eds.) [PDF]((http://arxiv.org/pdf/1305.3865v1.pdf)
Summary Recent research has shown the deep impact of the dynamics of human interactions (or temporal social networks) on the spreading of information, opinion formation, etc. In general, the bursty nature of human interactions lowers the interaction between people to the extent that both the speed and reach of information diffusion are diminished.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are you a social keeper or a social explorer?</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-05-03-are-you-a-social-keeper-or-a-social-explorer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2013 13:16:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-05-03-are-you-a-social-keeper-or-a-social-explorer/</guid>
      <description>In our last (just accepted) paper “Limited communication capacity unveils strategies for human interaction” [link] we have found that we humans have different social strategies when we communicate/interact with people. Specifically, the sociability of a person (the total number of contacts in a time interval) which is usually taken as the connectivity in the social network is actually the result of two different human features:
 Social capacity: the number of relationships humans can maintain opened and which is limited Social activity: the number of relationships human form and destroy as a consequence of their daily tasks, family, events, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La ciencia de la caballería andante</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2013/04/la-ciencia-de-la-caballeria-andante/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 07:15:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2013/04/la-ciencia-de-la-caballeria-andante/</guid>
      <description>Happy World Book Day
La Caballería andante (...) es una ciencia, dijo Don Quijote (...) que encierra en sí todas o las más ciencias del mundo (...) el que la profesa ha de ser jurisperito, y saber las leyes de la justicia distributiva y conmutativa (...) ha de ser teólogo, para saber dar razón de la cristiana ley que profesa (...); ha de ser médico, principalmente herbolario, parara conocer (...) las yerbas que tienen virtud de sanar las heridas (.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The predictability of consumer visitation patterns</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-04-18-the-predictability-of-consumer-visitation-patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2013 20:23:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-04-18-the-predictability-of-consumer-visitation-patterns/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Coco Krumme, Alejandro Llorente, Manuel Cebrian, Alex (&amp;ldquo;Sandy&amp;rdquo;) Pentland &amp;amp; Esteban Moro
Journal: Sci. Rep. 3, 1645; (2013). LINK
Abstract: We consider hundreds of thousands of individual economic transactions to ask: how predictable are consumers in their merchant visitation patterns? Our results suggest that, in the long-run, much of our seemingly elective activity is actually highly predictable. Notwithstanding a wide range of individual preferences, shoppers share regularities in how they visit merchant locations over time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limited communication capacity unveils strategies for human interaction</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-04-09-limited-communication-capacity-unveils-strategies-for-human-interaction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2013 07:43:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-04-09-limited-communication-capacity-unveils-strategies-for-human-interaction/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Giovanna Miritello, Rubén Lara, Manuel Cebrián and Esteban Moro
Journal: Scientific Reports 3, 1950 (2013). LINK
Abstract: Social connectivity is the key process that characterizes the structural properties of social networks and in turn processes such as navigation, influence or information diffusion. Since time, attention and cognition are inelastic resources, humans should have a predefined strategy to manage their social interactions over time. However, the limited observational length of existing human interaction datasets, together with the bursty nature of dyadic communications have hampered the observation of tie dynamics in social networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limits of social mobilization</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-04-01-limits-of-social-mobilization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 20:37:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-04-01-limits-of-social-mobilization/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Alex Rutherford, Manuel Cebrian, Sohan Dsouza, Esteban Moro, Alex Pentland, and Iyad Rahwan
Journal: PNAS 110 (16), 6281-6286 (2013) LINK
Abstract: The Internet and social media have enabled the mobilization of large crowds to achieve time-critical feats, ranging from mapping crises in real time, to organizing mass rallies, to conducting search-and-rescue operations over large geographies. Despite significant success, selection bias may lead to inflated expectations of the efficacy of social mobilization for these tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>when does emulation count as explanation?</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2013/03/when-does-emulation-count-as-explanation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 18:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2013/03/when-does-emulation-count-as-explanation/</guid>
      <description>To me, the main question when modeling a process in the social sciences is &amp;quot;when does emulation count as explanation?&amp;quot;
&amp;mdash; John Myles White (@johnmyleswhite) March 25, 2013  Interesting question. I guess the problem is that sometimes in science a model does not pretend to make any prediction, neither is supported by any relevant data. It simply emulates reality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time as a limited resource: Communication Strategy in Mobile Phone Networks</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-01-14-time-as-a-limited-resource-communication-strategy-in-mobile-phone-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 08:52:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2013-01-14-time-as-a-limited-resource-communication-strategy-in-mobile-phone-networks/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Giovanna Miritello, Esteban Moro, Rubén Lara, Rocío Martínez-López, Sam G. B. Roberts, Robin I. M. Dunbar
Journal: Social Networks 35, 89 (2013) LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We used a large database of 9 billion calls from 20 million mobile users to examine the relationships between aggregated time spent on the phone, personal network size, tiestrength and the way in which users distributed their limited time across their network (disparity). Compared to those with smaller networks, those with large networks did not devote proportionally more time to communication and had on average weaker ties (as measured by time spent communicating).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal networks with igraph and R (with 20 lines of code!)</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-11-10-temporal-networks-with-igraph-and-r-with-20-lines-of-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2012 23:55:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-11-10-temporal-networks-with-igraph-and-r-with-20-lines-of-code/</guid>
      <description>**UPDATE**: the version of the R code in this post does not work with newer versions of the igraph package (\ 1.0). I have posted an updated version of this post here: [Temporal networks with R and igraph (updated)](/post/2015-12-21-temporal-networks-with-r-and-igraph-updated/). Please visit the new post to use the new code and follow the discussion there.  In my last post about how a twitter conversation unfolds in time on Twitter, the dynamical nature of information diffusion in twitter was illustrated with a video of the temporal network of interactions (RTs) between accounts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preferential attachment: be first</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/11/preferential-attachment-be-first/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 00:29:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/11/preferential-attachment-be-first/</guid>
      <description>Preferential attachment is a key process governing the dynamics of many economic, social and biological process. It is the “The rich get richer” mechanism by which a quantity is distributed among individuals according to how much they already have. It also happens in social networks and the ones that have more social connectivity (the “hubs”) receive more new connections than the poorly connected. In a famous paper, Laszlo Barabási and Reka Albert encoded this mechanics in the so called Barabasi-Albert model to generate random scale free-networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal network of information diffusion in Twitter</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-10-29-temporal-network-of-information-diffusion-in-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2012 21:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-10-29-temporal-network-of-information-diffusion-in-twitter/</guid>
      <description>Millions of tweets, retweets and mentions are exchanged in Twitter everyday about very different subjects, events, opinions, etc. While aggregating this data over a time window might help to understand some properties of those processes in online social networks, the speed of information diffusion around particular time-bound events requires a temporal analysis of them. To show that (and with the help of the Text &amp;amp; Opinion Mining Group at IIC) we collected all tweets (750k) of the vibrant conversation around the disputed subject of the general strike of March 29th in Spain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms and Management</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/10/algorithms-and-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 08:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/10/algorithms-and-management/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I gave a talk in the 6th IIC Technology Conference about how Social Contagion can be leveraged for marketing purposes. The motto of the conference was about the need of using Algorithms in nowadays business process. With the availability of more and more complex data the use of algorithms that can detect and reduce complexity is of paramount importance. Big data is not only about volume (TeraBytes of data), it is about huge complex data and reducing that complexity can only be achieved by modeling, simulating and analyzing the patterns we observe in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Human Preferences Using the Block Structure of Complex Social Networks</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-09-12-predicting-human-preferences-using-the-block-structure-of-complex-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2012 12:19:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-09-12-predicting-human-preferences-using-the-block-structure-of-complex-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Roger Guimerà, Alejandro Llorente, Esteban Moro y Marta Sales-Pardo
Journal: PLoS ONE 7, e44620 (2012) LINK
Abstract: With ever-increasing available data, predicting individuals&#39; preferences and helping them locate the most relevant information has become a pressing need. Understanding and predicting preferences is also important from a fundamental point of view, as part of what has been called a “new” computational social science. Here, we propose a novel approach based on stochastic block models, which have been developed by sociologists as plausible models of complex networks of social interactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It was a delicious assignment, infinitely complicated</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/08/it-was-a-delicious-assignment-infinitely-complicated/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2012 16:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/08/it-was-a-delicious-assignment-infinitely-complicated/</guid>
      <description>I have just read an amazing book &amp;ldquo;Shibumi&amp;rdquo; by Trevanian (a.k.a. Rodney William Whitaker) probably the best spy novel I have read so far. In the book, a big data computer (called Fat Boy) is operated by a &amp;ldquo;data scientist&amp;rdquo; (although is not called that way). I enjoyed very much the following paragraph, an analogy of the emptiness of big data without insight and also a musing about how difficult is to find relationships from activity data (the kind of research we do!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Which chart to use</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/08/which-chart-to-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2012 10:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2012/08/which-chart-to-use/</guid>
      <description>In most of my talks I present quantitative evidence of patterns, data exploration or results. But which is the right way to show that evidence? Worry no more: the Extreme Presentation Method helps you to decide with this chart chooser (click here to download the pdf)

My impression is that this chart chooser is good for small data. For big data some of the charts render useless. For example, read the insightfull post Don&amp;rsquo;t use Scatterplots by Chris Stucchio on why is not a good idea to use scatterplots to show relationship between bivariate data when you have large amounts of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agent-specific impact of single trades in financial markets</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-03-12-agent-specific-impact-of-single-trades-in-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 21:12:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-03-12-agent-specific-impact-of-single-trades-in-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Alex Bladon, Esteban Moro y Tobias Galla
Journal: Physical Review E 85, 036103 (2012) LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We present an analysis of the price impact associated with single trades effected by different financial firms. Using data from the Spanish Stock Market, we find a high degree of heterogeneity across different market members, both in the instantaneous impact functions and in the time-dependent market response to trades by individual members.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Branching dynamics of viral information spreading</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-11-03-branching-dynamics-of-viral-information-spreading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 09:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-11-03-branching-dynamics-of-viral-information-spreading/</guid>
      <description>Authors: José Luis Iribarren and Esteban Moro
Journal: Physical Review E 84, 046116 (2011) LINK | arXiv
Abstract: Despite its importance for rumors or innovations propagation, peer-to-peer collaboration, social networking, or marketing, the dynamics of information spreading is not well understood. Since the diffusion depends on the heterogeneous patterns of human behavior and is driven by the participants’ decisions, its propagation dynamics shows surprising properties not explained by traditional epidemic or contagion models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Features of Online Networks: The Strength of Intermediary Ties in Online Social Media</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-07-21-social-features-of-online-networks-the-strength-of-weak-ties-in-online-social-media/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2011 09:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-07-21-social-features-of-online-networks-the-strength-of-weak-ties-in-online-social-media/</guid>
      <description>Authors: P. A. Grabowicz, J. J. Ramasco, E. Moro, J. P. Pujol and V. M. Eguiluz
Journal: PLoS ONE 7(1): e29358 (2012). LINK
Abstract: An increasing fraction of today’s social interactions occur using online social media as communication channels. Recent worldwide events, such as social movements in Spain or revolts in the Middle East, highlight their capacity to boost people’s coordination. Online networks display in general a rich internal structure where users can choose among different types and intensity of interactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter y Política: Información, Opinión y ¿Predicción?</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-06-17-twitter-y-politica-informacion-opinion-y-prediccion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2011 10:56:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-06-17-twitter-y-politica-informacion-opinion-y-prediccion/</guid>
      <description>Authors: M. Luz Congosto, Montse Fernández y Esteban Moro
Journal: Cuadernos de Comunicación Evoca 4 (2011). LINK
Abstract: Estamos a las puertas de una nueva manera de medir la opinión política: mediante la conversación en Red, que permite no sólo conocer el feedback de los ciudadanos a la política, sino también la imagen de los políticos que se refleja en la Red, la dinámica de opinión en comunidades o grupos y el efecto de los diferentes medios de comunicación en dicha conversación.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complex Dynamics of Human Interactions, September 14th 2011</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2011/03/complex-dynamics-of-human-interactions-september-14th-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 14:51:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2011/03/complex-dynamics-of-human-interactions-september-14th-2011/</guid>
      <description>We (together with Kimmo Kaski, Aalto University) are organizing the ECCS&#39;11 Satellite conference &amp;ldquo;Complex Dynamics of Human Interactions&amp;rdquo; to be held at Vienna, September 14th.
You can find more info at http://www.complexdynamics.org
&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not enough to have a map of the structure. It is crucial to understand the dynamics of a process”, L. Barábasi
Scope The nature of human interaction has undergone a substantial change in the past years and the change does not seem to be over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Affinity Paths and information diffusion in social networks</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-02-08-affinity-paths-and-information-diffusion-in-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2011 09:42:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2011-02-08-affinity-paths-and-information-diffusion-in-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>Authors: José Luis Iribarren and Esteban Moro
Journal: Social Networks 33, 134-142 (2011). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: Widespread interest in the diffusion of information through social networks has produced a large number of Social Dynamics models. A majority of them use theoretical hypothesis to explain their diffusion mechanisms while the few empirically based ones average out their measures over many messages of different contents. Our empirical research tracking the step-by-step email propagation of an invariable viral marketing message delves into the content impact and has discovered new and striking features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical strength of social ties in information spreading</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2010-11-25-the-dynamical-strength-of-social-ties-in-information-spreading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2010 10:19:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2010-11-25-the-dynamical-strength-of-social-ties-in-information-spreading/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Giovanna Miritello, Esteban Moro y Rubén Lara
Journal: Physical Review E (Rapid Comm) 83, 045102 (2011). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We investigate the temporal patterns of human communication and its influence on the spreading of information in social networks. The analysis of mobile phone calls of 20 million people in one country shows that human communication is bursty and happens in group conversations. These features have opposite effects in information reach: while bursts hinder propagation at large scales, conversations favor local rapid cascades.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relationship mining</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2010/01/relationship-mining/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2010 09:16:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2010/01/relationship-mining/</guid>
      <description>Each day trillions of emails, phone calls, comments on blogs, twitter messages, exchanges in online social networks, etc. are done. Not only the number of communications has increased, but also each of these transactions leaves a digital trace that can be recorded to reconstruct our high-frequency human activity. It is not only the amount and variety of data that is recorded what is important. Also its high-frequency character and its comprehensive nature have allowed researchers, companies and agencies to investigate individual and group dynamics at an unprecedented level of detail and applied them to client modeling, organizational analysis or epidemic spreading [1].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La ciencia española no necesita tijeras</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/10/la-ciencia-espanola-no-necesita-tijeras/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2009 06:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/10/la-ciencia-espanola-no-necesita-tijeras/</guid>
      <description>La crisis y su efecto en los presupuestos del año 2010 han servido para poner a prueba el compromiso del gobierno de cambiar de modelo productivo y aumentar el gasto en I+D+i. En especial, sufren recortes los gastos del ministerio de Ciencia e Innovación (hasta un 17%), el capítulo 7 (las subvenciones a investigadores) un 17% y los presupuestos de algunos OPIs dependientes del Ministerio con un 15% menos de media.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The speed and reach of forwarded emails, rumors, and hoaxes in electronic social networks</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/08/the-speed-and-reach-of-forwarded-emails-rumors-and-hoaxes-in-electronic-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2009 11:23:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/08/the-speed-and-reach-of-forwarded-emails-rumors-and-hoaxes-in-electronic-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>We have just published an experimental/theoretical work on the speed of information diffusion in social networks in Physical Review Letters. Specifically we have studied the impact of the heterogeneity of human activity in propagation of emails, rumors, hoaxes, etc. Tracking email marketing campaigns, executed by IBM Corporation in 11 European countries, we were able to compare their viral propagation with our theory (see below the campaigns details).
The results are very simple.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Market impact and trading profile of large trading orders in stock markets</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-08-04-market-impact-and-trading-proefac81le-of-large-trading-orders-in-stock-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2009 08:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-08-04-market-impact-and-trading-proefac81le-of-large-trading-orders-in-stock-markets/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro, Javier Vicente, Luis G. Moyano, Austin Gerig, J. Doyne Farmer, Gabriella Vaglica, Fabrizio Lillo and Rosario N. Mantegna
Journal: Phys. Rev. E 80, 066102 (2009) LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We empirically study the market impact of trading orders. We are speciﬁcally interested in large trading orders that are executed incrementally, which we call hidden orders. These are reconstructed based on information about market member codes using data from the Spanish Stock Market and the London Stock Exchange.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Human Activity Patterns on the Dynamics of Information Diffusion</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-08-04-impact-of-human-activity-patterns-on-the-dynamics-of-information-diffusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2009 07:59:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-08-04-impact-of-human-activity-patterns-on-the-dynamics-of-information-diffusion/</guid>
      <description>Authors: J. L. Iribarren and E. Moro
Journal: Physical Review Letters 103, 038702 (2009) LINK arXiv
Abstract: We study the impact of human activity patterns on information diffusion. To this end we ran a viral email experiment involving 31183 individuals in which we were able to track a speciﬁc piece of information through the social network. We found that, contrary to traditional models, information travels at an unexpectedly slow pace. By using a branching model which accurately describes the experiment, we show that the large heterogeneity found in the response time is responsible for the slow dynamics of information at the collective level.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving a talk</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/07/giving-a-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2009 09:06:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/07/giving-a-talk/</guid>
      <description>Giving a good talk is not an easy task, but with time and practice you get to learn how to communicate (hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ve learned too!!). There are a number of places on the web with advices to give a good talk. But I like Paul N. Edwards&amp;rsquo;s short manual about how to give an academic talk. My experience as audience in many talks tell me that the most important things are (quoting Paul&amp;rsquo;s manual):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ph.D. offer... interested?</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/06/phd-offer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2009 10:06:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/06/phd-offer/</guid>
      <description>Our research group is looking for Ph.D. candidates. Here is the announcement
![mosaico](http://estebanmoro.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/mosaico.jpg) We offer contracts to work for a Ph.D. within the project MOSAICO (Modelling, Analysis and Simulations of Complex Systems). Candidates must have a degree in physics, math or related disciplines with outstanding marks. Info on the research lines is available from [http://www.gisc.es](http://www.gisc.es) and work will be carried out at Universities Complutense or Carlos III de Madrid. Work will begin on October 1st, 2009.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The probability of going through a bad patch</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/04/the-probability-of-going-through-a-bad-patch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2009 11:37:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/04/the-probability-of-going-through-a-bad-patch/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ve heard it: people that invest on the stock market or that gamble in lotteries, casinos, etc usually say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going through a bad patch&amp;rdquo; (or bad spell). That is, they have been losing money for a while, but hey! better times are ahead and there&amp;rsquo;s no reason to quit. Are they sure? Are better times ahead? How close is &amp;ldquo;ahead&amp;rdquo; to today? Let&amp;rsquo;s work through a specific example to see how far is &amp;ldquo;ahead&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Being part of &#34;best of 2008&#34;</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/03/being-part-of-best-of-2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2009 06:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/03/being-part-of-best-of-2008/</guid>
      <description>I got wonderful news today. Our paper &amp;ldquo;Specialization and herding behavior of trading firms in a financial market&amp;rdquo; (pdf) has been selected by the Editorial Board of New Journal of Physics as part of the Journal&amp;rsquo;s Best of 2008. According to their site, &amp;ldquo;Best of 2008&amp;rdquo; is a compilation of articles selected by the Editorial Board and staff team on the basis of criteria including referee endorsements, readership and citation levels and simple broad appeal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The use of statistics</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/02/the-use-of-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Feb 2009 08:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/02/the-use-of-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Mark Twain (1924) probably had politicians in mind when he reiterated Disraeli’s famous remark (&#34;There are three kinds of lies: lies, damned lies and statistics&#34;). Scientists, we hope, would never use data in such a selective manner to suit their own ends. But, alas, the analysis of data is often the source of some exasperation even in an academic context. On hearing comments like ‘the result of this experiment was inconclusive, so we had to use statistics’, we are frequently left wondering as to what strange tricks have been played on the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Itô calculus for the rest of us</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-02-12-ito-calculus-for-the-rest-of-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2009 08:21:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-02-12-ito-calculus-for-the-rest-of-us/</guid>
      <description>One of the areas of my research is stochastic differential equations (SDE). I posted about it several times before. One of the things students and collaborators keep asking me about SDEs is the weird stochastic Itô Calculus. Itô Calculus is different from what you learn in 101 calculus. In particular, the chain rule is not longer valid. Let me explain it with an example. Suppose you have the following equation</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing citation networks</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/02/visualizing-citation-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2009 17:51:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/02/visualizing-citation-networks/</guid>
      <description>The Eigenfactor Project and Moritz Stefaner join efforts to visualize the citation network between different journals belonging to different research fields. It is amazing and a wonderful way to explore patterns in citation networks
 Found via FlowingData</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waiting for the bus</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-01-28-waiting-for-the-bus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2009 10:54:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-01-28-waiting-for-the-bus/</guid>
      <description>Although the public transportation system in Madrid is very good, I don&amp;rsquo;t usually take the bus or the train to move around. But sometimes my car decides I should take public transportation (bus or train). One of things I always found intriguing is that I always wait way more for the bus than what is expected according to the frequency quoted by the transportation companies at the bus or train stop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Referee Reports</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/01/referee-reports/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2009 10:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/01/referee-reports/</guid>
      <description>I found an interesting presentation by Sami Mitra, associate editor of Physical Review Letters, about the editorial office and the editorial process at PRL. Among some interesting figures about the journal and also about the procedure of selecting potential referees, I enjoyed very much the quotes from some of the referee communications with the editorial office. Here they are:
 I cannot review this paper as it is wrong and I did it first.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publish and... perish</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/01/publish-and-perish/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2009 08:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/01/publish-and-perish/</guid>
      <description>In the old days, research quality was measured by the number of papers you published. Publishing was a hard process and only few scientists were able to publish several papers per year. However, with the bloom of new journals, the appearance of electronic editorial process, and the specialization of research fields, the number of publications per year has grow exponentially during the last decades. Thus publishing is not longer a good measure of the quality of research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The best job in 2008 was ... mathematician!</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/01/the-best-job-in-2008-is-mathematician/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 10:46:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2009/01/the-best-job-in-2008-is-mathematician/</guid>
      <description>Good news to fans of the &amp;ldquo;language of Nature&amp;rdquo;, mathematics. Wall Street Journal is running an article on what are the best jobs in 2008. The ranking is done &amp;ldquo;evaluating 200 professions to determine the best and worst according to five criteria inherent to every job: environment, income, employment outlook, physical demands and stress.&amp;rdquo; And which one do you think ranks first? Here is the list of the first ten:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brown&#39;s observations on Brownian motion </title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/browns-observations-on-brownian-motion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2008 09:27:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/browns-observations-on-brownian-motion/</guid>
      <description>In 1828, Robert Brown published the manuscript entitled &amp;ldquo;A brief account of microscopical observations made in the months of June, July and August 1827, on the particles contained in the pollen of plants; and on the general existence of active molecules in organic and inorganic bodies&amp;rdquo; in the Edinburgh new Philosophical Journal [download it in pdf format here]. He suspended some of the pollen grains of the species Clarkia pulchella in water and examined them closely, only to see them &amp;ldquo;filled with particles&amp;rdquo; of around 5 µm diameter that were &amp;ldquo;very evidently in motion&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science is the only news</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/science-is-the-only-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2008 08:19:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/science-is-the-only-news/</guid>
      <description>Science is the only news. When you scan through a newspaper or magazine, all the human interest stuff is the same old he-said-she-said, the politics and economics the same sorry cyclic dramas, the fashions a pathetic illusion of newness, and even the technology is predictable if you know the science. Human nature doesn’t change much; science does, and the change accrues, altering the world irreversibly.  A famous quote by Stewart Brand, that appear in John Brockman&amp;rsquo;s essay (and book) The Third Culture</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New section in the arXiv: Quantitative Finance</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/new-section-in-the-arxiv-quantitative-finance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2008 09:05:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/new-section-in-the-arxiv-quantitative-finance/</guid>
      <description>News from the arXiv: a new section has been created to host preprints about Quantitative Finance. The section (as stated in the press release) intends to fix a problem with existing pre-print repositories. One one hand, social sciences repositories like SSRN, RepEC/IDEAS and others are too academic for practitioners, while on the other hand sites like defaultrisk.com or wilmott.com have not attracted many academic contributors. The new category in the arXiv would be a gathering point for both practitioners and academic people working in this important research field</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to stochastic differential equations</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/introduction-to-stochastic-differential-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2008 16:45:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/introduction-to-stochastic-differential-equations/</guid>
      <description>Stochastic differential equations (SDEs) are basically inhomogenous ordinary differential equations that depend on an external stochastic process.
Typically, that stochastic process is white noise, which is the mathematical idealization of the noise found in nature. This idealization is handy, because it simplifies the mathematical description. However, this idealization comes at some cost: traditional calculus is no longer valid and you have to use the so-call Itô calculus. This introduces some non intuitive changes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Percentages and absolute numbers</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/percentages-and-absolute-numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2008 09:47:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/percentages-and-absolute-numbers/</guid>
      <description>Percentage of active users in the Internet 2.0 is tiny. Fractions go from
 * only 1% of Wikipedia&#39;s users contribute to making it better * only 0.1% of users upload their own videos to Youtube * only 3% of people with weblogs post on a daily basis * only 1% of Amazon.com customers contribute with reviews  The numbers are tiny. But not uncommon. Typical return rates of marketing campaigns or surveys are around 2-5% (see report by the Direct Marketing Association).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Game Theory a scientific theory?</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/is-game-theory-a-scientific-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2008 07:40:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/12/is-game-theory-a-scientific-theory/</guid>
      <description>A wonderful quote about the nature of Game Theory
Game theory is no doubt wonderful for telling stories. However, it flunks the main test of any scientific theory: The ability to make empirically testable predictions. In most real-life situations, many different outcomes -- from full cooperation to near-disastrous conflict -- are consistent with the game-theory version of rationality.  by Michael Mandel, on Kahneman and Smith 2002 Nobel Prize in Economics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kiyoshi Itô, 93, dies</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/11/kiyoshi-ito-93-dies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2008 22:17:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/11/kiyoshi-ito-93-dies/</guid>
      <description>November was a rather sad month in the world of stochastic differential equations. In the 26th we were suppose to be celebrating the birth of one of the best mathematicians in history, Norbert Wiener, who gives name to the Wiener process, usually denoted W(t). However, in the 10th, Kiyoshi Itô, the father of stochastic differential equations, passed away. Interestingly both are present in a simple stochastic differential equation like this</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individuals and groups</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/11/individuals-and-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2008 15:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2008/11/individuals-and-groups/</guid>
      <description>While the individual man is an insoluble puzzle, in the aggregate he becomes a mathematical certainty. You can, for example, never foretell what any one man will do, but you can say with precision what an average number will be up to. Individuals vary, but percentages remain constant. So says the statistician Sherlock Holmes in &amp;ldquo;The Sign of Four&amp;rdquo;. Via Gaussianos</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proofs and pictures </title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2007/11/proofs-and-pictures/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2007 20:18:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2007/11/proofs-and-pictures/</guid>
      <description>A picture is worth a thousand lines of equations
By James Robert Brown</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Specialization of strategies and herding behavior of trading firms in a financial market</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2007-07-04-specialization-of-strategies-and-herding-behavior-of-trading-firms-in-a-financial-market/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jul 2007 20:19:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2007-07-04-specialization-of-strategies-and-herding-behavior-of-trading-firms-in-a-financial-market/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Fabrizio Lillo, Esteban Moro, Gabriella Vaglica y Rosario Mantegna
Journal: New Journal of Physics 10 (2008) 043019 LINK arXiv
Abstract: Agent-based models of ﬁnancial markets usually make assumptions about agent&amp;rsquo;s preferred stylized strategies. Empirical validations of these assumptions have not been performed so far on a full-market scale. Here we present a comprehensive study of the resulting strategies followed by the ﬁrms which are members of the Spanish Stock Exchange.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Information diffusion epidemics in social networks</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2007-06-06-information-diffusion-epidemics-in-social-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2007 07:37:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2007-06-06-information-diffusion-epidemics-in-social-networks/</guid>
      <description>Authors: José Luis Iribarren, Esteban Moro
Journal: Preprint 0706.0641 arXiv
Abstract: The dynamics of information dissemination in social networks is of paramount importance in processes such as rumors or fads propagation, spread of product innovations or &amp;ldquo;word-of-mouth&amp;rdquo; communications. Due to the difficulty in tracking a specific information when it is transmitted by people, most understanding of information spreading in social networks comes from models or indirect measurements. Here we present an integrated experimental and theoretical framework to understand and quantitatively predict how and when information spreads over social networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scaling laws of strategic behavior and size heterogeneity in agent dynamics</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2007-04-20-scaling-laws-of-strategic-behavior-and-size-heterogeneity-in-agent-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2007 09:54:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2007-04-20-scaling-laws-of-strategic-behavior-and-size-heterogeneity-in-agent-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Gabriella Vaglica, Fabrizio Lillo, Esteban Moro y Rosario N. Mantegna
Journal: Physical Review E 77, 036110 (2008). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: The dynamics of many socioeconomic systems is determined by the decision making process of agents. The decision process depends on agent&amp;rsquo;s characteristics, such as preferences, risk aversion, behavioral biases, etc. In addition, in some systems the size of agents can be highly heterogeneous leading to very different impacts of agents on the system dynamics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Editor de la sección &#34;Física y Computación&#34;</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/editor-de-la-seccion-fisica-y-computacion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2006 20:21:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/editor-de-la-seccion-fisica-y-computacion/</guid>
      <description>Hola a todos.
Este es mi primer post en español en este blog (aunque incluyo la traducción al inglés más abajo). Y lo hago para anunciar que soy el editor desde el número de Diciembre de la sección &amp;ldquo;Física y Computación&amp;rdquo; de la revista de la Real Sociedad Española de Física. Para seguir las novedades y noticias de dicha sección he montado un blog (distinto a este) en el que podeis ver los nuevos artículos de la sección, así como el archivo de los artículos ya publicados.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivy Live!</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/superconductivy-live/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2006 08:09:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/superconductivy-live/</guid>
      <description>It is always amazing to browse through YouTube, specially if you are looking for science material. Here is an example of superconductivity: take a superconductor and a magnet at room temperature. Nothing happens. Now cool down the superconductor using liquid nitrogen. The superconductor starts &amp;ldquo;superconducting&amp;rdquo; and boom! here comes in the Meissner effect. As always, a picture (movie) is better than a page of equations to show how wonderful physics is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The theory of nothing</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/the-theory-of-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2006 07:24:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/the-theory-of-nothing/</guid>
      <description>Two New York newspapers (The New York Times and the New Yorker) are running stories about whether string theory is a theory of anything or not. Specifically, both articles are reviews of a couple of very critic books on string theory:  *  NOT EVEN WRONG : The Failure of String Theory and the Search for Unity in Physical Law. By Peter Woit.
 *  THE TROUBLE WITH PHYSICS The Rise of String Theory, the Fall of a Science, and What Comes Next.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The marketing of breaking laws of physics</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/the-marketing-of-breaking-laws-of-physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2006 08:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/10/the-marketing-of-breaking-laws-of-physics/</guid>
      <description>Apparently, a company in Ireland named Steorn has found the killer marketing campaign for their products:
 1. Get a law of physics: the first law of thermodynamics, for example, and claim you have a technology that can break it. Cool! 2. Get a good flashy marketing campaign by publishing in The Economist a &amp;quot;show us wrong&amp;quot; announcement to the scientific community. 3. Hide the details of your technology and delay its public announcement by creating a &amp;quot;challenge&amp;quot; to the scientific community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kiyoshi Itô wins the Gauss Prize</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/09/kiyoshi-ito-wins-the-gauss-prize/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2006 08:13:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/09/kiyoshi-ito-wins-the-gauss-prize/</guid>
      <description>Kiyoshi Itô (90), professor emeritus at kyoto University, has become the first winner of the Gauss Prize. This prize is to honor scientist whose mathematical research has had an impact outside mathematics. Ito&amp;rsquo;s work, mainly in establishing a well defined calculus (named Ito&amp;rsquo;s calculus) to treat high irregular noise functions has got widespread application in describing several stochastic processes across fields like economics, biology, chemistry, physics, etc. Ito&amp;rsquo;s calculus is behind the pricing of options introduced by Black, Scholes and Merton (which got them a Nobel price).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Seven Warning Signs of Bogus Science</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/04/the-seven-warning-signs-of-bogus-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2006 08:15:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/04/the-seven-warning-signs-of-bogus-science/</guid>
      <description>We all are aware of recent cases of fraud in science. The case of cloning in South Korea is the most recent one, but not the first or the last to happen. Identifying those cases is hard, since most of the times the verification of the claims is a long time-consuming process. Very recently, Robert L. Park has identified some warning signs about a scientific discoverythat can make us doubt about the scientific soundness of it, since they indicate that a scientific claim lies well outside the bounds of rational scientific discourse:  * The discoverer pitches the claim directly to the media * The discoverer says that a powerful establishment is trying to suppress his or her work * The scientific effect involved is always at the very limit of detection * Evidence for a discovery is anecdotal * The discoverer says a belief is credible because it has endured for centuries * The discoverer has worked in isolation * The discoverer must propose new laws of nature to explain an observation  Several examples with all or several of these red lights come to my mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The future of the science might be wiki</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/03/the-future-of-the-science-might-be-wiki/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2006 08:17:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/03/the-future-of-the-science-might-be-wiki/</guid>
      <description>The Edge has a summary-article on a Kevin Kelly’s talk on The Next 100 Years of Science: Long-term Trends in the Scientific Method. Kevin Kelly helped launch Wiredmagazine in 1993 and has published several books and articles in publications such as The Economist, The New York Times, Time, etc. He rises some interesting points about what’s next in science for this century. Specifically:

 * There will be more change in the next 50 years of science than in the last 400 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing bad letters of recommendation: the story of Bachelier and Lévy</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/03/writing-bad-letters-of-recommendation-the-story-of-bachelier-and-levy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2006 08:25:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/03/writing-bad-letters-of-recommendation-the-story-of-bachelier-and-levy/</guid>
      <description>Take a coin and toss it a number \(N\) of times in a time interval of duration \(T\). Suppose that every time you get head you win \(a\) euros and that you lose the same amount of money when you get tail. Then your capital is a random process with ups and dows like this:
 ![](/img/posts/figurebachelier.jpg) This process is a stochastic process usually called &amp;ldquo;Random Walk&amp;rdquo; and its properties depend on the parameters $N, a $ and \(T\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spreading of Viscous Fluid Drops on a Solid Substrate Assisted by Thermal Fluctuations</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2006-02-09-spreading-of-viscous-fluid-drops-on-a-solid-substrate-assisted-by-thermal-fluctuations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2006 09:19:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2006-02-09-spreading-of-viscous-fluid-drops-on-a-solid-substrate-assisted-by-thermal-fluctuations/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Benny Davidovitch, Esteban Moro, and Howard A. Stone
Journal: Physical Review Letters 95, 244505 (2005). LINK
Abstract: We study the spreading of viscous drops on a solid substrate, taking into account the effects of thermal fluctuations in the fluid momentum. A nonlinear stochastic lubrication equation is derived and studied using numerical simulations and scaling analysis. We show that asymptotically spreading drops admit self-similar shapes, whose average radii can increase at rates much faster than these predicted by Tanner’s law.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humans are superdiffusive</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/02/humans-are-superdiffusive/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2006 07:31:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/02/humans-are-superdiffusive/</guid>
      <description>When tea is poured in a cup of hot water, we observe a phenomenon called diffusion: in the end particles of tea spread evenly throughout the mass of water and we enjoy our cup of tea. Diffusion occurs as a result of the second law of thermodynamics (increase of entropy) and can be modeled quantitatively using the diffusion equation (or heat equation). This is a funny equation, since it establishes that the velocity of spreading is infinite while the mean root square fluctuations of the position of the particles grows in time as</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cum hoc ergo propter hoc</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/01/cum-hoc-ergo-propter-hoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2006 08:22:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2006/01/cum-hoc-ergo-propter-hoc/</guid>
      <description>Or… Correlation implies causality. This is a logical fallacy. Keep this in mind when analyzing data. There are numerous cases of how people use this logical fallacy nowadays (most typically in newspapers). For example, the following graph
shows a correlation between global warming and the number of remaining pirates. But this does not imply (of course), any causality between them.
By the way, this graph appears in a Bobby Henderson’s clever parody of the type of arguments in Intelligent Design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meet the glaciers</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/12/meet-the-glaciers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2005 07:35:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/12/meet-the-glaciers/</guid>
      <description>I have been on holidays during the last two weeks visiting Argentina. The picture above was taken on top of the Perito Moreno glacier, which is amazing. Most glaciers we found where blueish, including the icebergs found floating in the rivers. The reason for that is that the thicker the ice or snow layer is, the better red colors are absorbed by the layer and only the blue colors are reflected (see a more detailed explanation here).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Folding paper</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/11/folding-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2005 08:26:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/11/folding-paper/</guid>
      <description>You can’t fold a paper more than seven or eight times. Don’t believe me? Then try it. Thinner paper? Longer paper? It doesn’t matter; you just can’t do it. I used to play this game with my friends which were always amazed and asked for an explanation. Is there any physical or mathematical constrain to do it? Nope: it is simply a matter of scale. If you have a paper of length L and you fold it, the length now is L/2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I didn’t answer your email</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/11/why-i-didnt-answer-your-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2005 07:36:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/11/why-i-didnt-answer-your-email/</guid>
      <description>In a recent Nature article, Albert-Lászlo Barabási and João Gama Oliveira, have found the perfect excuse for lazy people not answering some emails in their inbox: they analyzed the time response of emails and found that they follow a power law probability distribution of the form P(t) = 1/t. In particular this implies that not even the mean response time is finite. Hey! why should you then expect me to answer your emails within my lifetime period!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A number to rank them all</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/11/a-number-to-rank-them-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2005 07:37:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/2005/11/a-number-to-rank-them-all/</guid>
      <description>UCSD physicist Jorge E. Hirsch has propose a quick-and-dirty way to measure quality of academic scientist’s output. His method is explained and studied in a paper to be published in the November 15 issue of PNAS. The idea is very simple and it is called the h-index. This number relies on the number of citations our papers have. In particular the h-index is the maximum number h that verifies the following: at least h of papers of an author have h citations each.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boundary preserving semi-analytical numerical algorithms for stochastic differential equations</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2005-08-01-boundary-preserving-semi-analytical-numerical-algorithms-for-stochastic-differential-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2005 07:40:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2005-08-01-boundary-preserving-semi-analytical-numerical-algorithms-for-stochastic-differential-equations/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro and Henri Schurz
Journal: SIAM Journal of Scientific Computing, Volume 29 Issue 4, Pages 1525-1549 (2007). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: Construction of splitting-step methods and properties of related non-negativity andboundary preserving numerical algorithms for solving stochastic differential equations (SDEs) of Ito-type are discussed. We present convergence proofs for a newly designed splitting-step algorithm and simulation studies for numerous numerical examples ranging from stochastic dynamics occurring in asset pricing theory in mathematical finance (SDEs of CIR and CEV models) to measure-valued diffusion and superBrownian motion (SPDEs) as met in biology and physics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical schemes for continuum models of reaction-diffusion systems subject to internal noise</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2004-10-23-numerical-schemes-for-continuum-models-of-reaction-diffusion-systems-subject-to-internal-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Oct 2004 09:41:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2004-10-23-numerical-schemes-for-continuum-models-of-reaction-diffusion-systems-subject-to-internal-noise/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro
Journal: Physical Review E (Rapid Communication) 70, 045102 (2004). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We present numerical schemes to integrate stochastic partial differential equations which describe the spatiotemporal dynamics of reaction-diffusion problems under the effect of internal fluctuations. The schemes conserve the non-negativity of the solutions and incorporate the Poissonian nature of internal fluctuations at small densities, their performance being limited by the level of approximation of density fluctuations at small scales.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Minority Game: an introductory guide</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2004-08-31-the-minority-game-an-introductory-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2004 21:23:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2004-08-31-the-minority-game-an-introductory-guide/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro
Book: Advances in Condensed Matter and __Statistical Physics, _E. Korutcheva and R. Cuerno eds. (Nova Science Publishers, New York 2004). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: The Minority Game is a simple model for the collective behavior of agents in an idealized situation where they have to compete through adaptation for a finite resource. This review summarizes the statistical mechanics community efforts to clear up and understand the behavior of this model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid method for simulating front propagation in reaction-diffusion systems</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2004-06-01-hybrid-method-for-simulating-front-propagation-in-reaction-diffusion-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2004 09:56:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2004-06-01-hybrid-method-for-simulating-front-propagation-in-reaction-diffusion-systems/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro
Journal: Physical Review E, Rapid Communication 69, 060101 (2004). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We study the propagation of pulled fronts in the \(A\leftrightarrow A+A\) microscopic reaction-diffusion process using Monte Carlo simulations. In the mean field approximation the process is described by the deterministic Fisher-Kolmogorov-Petrovsky-Piscounov equation. In particular, we concentrate on the corrections to the deterministic behavior due to the number of particles per correlated volume \(\Omega\). By means of a hybrid simulation scheme, we manage to reach large macroscopic values of \(\Omega\), which allows us to show the importance in the dynamics of microscopic pulled fronts of the interplay of microscopic fluctuations and their macroscopic relaxation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of pulled fronts in fermionic microscopic particle models</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2003-08-25-emergence-of-pulled-fronts-in-fermionic-microscopic-particle-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2003 09:44:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2003-08-25-emergence-of-pulled-fronts-in-fermionic-microscopic-particle-models/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro
Phys. Rev. E, Rapid Communication, 68, 025102 (2003). LINK | arXiv
Abstract:
We study the emergence and dynamics of pulled fronts described by the Fisher-Kolmogorov-Petrovsky-Piscounov (FKPP) equation in the microscopic reaction-diffusion process \(A\leftrightarrow A+A\) on the lattice when only a particle is allowed per site. To this end we identify the parameter that controls the strength of internal fluctuations in this model, namely, the number of particles per correlated volume.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defect formation in the Swift-Hohenberg equation</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2003-03-11-defect-formation-in-the-swift-hohenberg-equation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2003 09:45:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2003-03-11-defect-formation-in-the-swift-hohenberg-equation/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Tobias Galla and Esteban Moro
Journal: Phys. Rev. E, Rapid Communication 67, 035101 (2003). LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We study numerically and analytically the dynamics of defect formation during a finite-time quench of the two-dimensional Swift-Hohenberg (SH) model of Rayleigh-Bénard convection. We find that the Kibble-Zurek picture of defect formation can be applied to describe the density of defects produced during the quench. Our study reveals the relevance of two factors: the effect of local variations of the striped patterns within defect-free domains and the presence of both pointlike and extended defects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internal Fluctuations Effects on Fisher Waves</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2001-11-14-internal-fluctuations-effects-on-fisher-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2001 09:55:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2001-11-14-internal-fluctuations-effects-on-fisher-waves/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro
Journal: Physical Review Letters 87, 238303 (2001) LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We study the diffusion-limited reaction \(A \leftrightarrow A = A\) in various spatial dimensions to observe the effect of internal fluctuations on the interface between stable and unstable phases. We find that, similar to what has been observed in d = 1 dimensions, internal fluctuations modify the mean-field predictions for this process, which is given by Fisher’s reaction-diffusion equation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
