<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Market Impact on </title>
    <link>https://estebanmoro.org/tags/market-impact/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Market Impact on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 21:12:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://estebanmoro.org/tags/market-impact/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Agent-specific impact of single trades in financial markets</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-03-12-agent-specific-impact-of-single-trades-in-financial-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 21:12:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2012-03-12-agent-specific-impact-of-single-trades-in-financial-markets/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Alex Bladon, Esteban Moro y Tobias Galla
Journal: Physical Review E 85, 036103 (2012) LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We present an analysis of the price impact associated with single trades effected by different financial firms. Using data from the Spanish Stock Market, we find a high degree of heterogeneity across different market members, both in the instantaneous impact functions and in the time-dependent market response to trades by individual members.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Market impact and trading profile of large trading orders in stock markets</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-08-04-market-impact-and-trading-proefac81le-of-large-trading-orders-in-stock-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2009 08:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2009-08-04-market-impact-and-trading-proefac81le-of-large-trading-orders-in-stock-markets/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Esteban Moro, Javier Vicente, Luis G. Moyano, Austin Gerig, J. Doyne Farmer, Gabriella Vaglica, Fabrizio Lillo and Rosario N. Mantegna
Journal: Phys. Rev. E 80, 066102 (2009) LINK | arXiv
Abstract: We empirically study the market impact of trading orders. We are speciﬁcally interested in large trading orders that are executed incrementally, which we call hidden orders. These are reconstructed based on information about market member codes using data from the Spanish Stock Market and the London Stock Exchange.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
