<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Segregation on </title>
    <link>https://estebanmoro.org/tags/segregation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Segregation on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://estebanmoro.org/tags/segregation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity beyond density: Experienced social mixing of urban streets</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-03-diversity-beyond-density-experienced-social-mixing-of-urban-streets/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-03-diversity-beyond-density-experienced-social-mixing-of-urban-streets/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Authors&lt;/em&gt;: Zhuangyuan Fan, Tianyu Su, Maoran Sun, Ariel Noyman, Fan Zhang, Alex ‘Sandy’ Pentland, Esteban Moro&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Publication&lt;/em&gt;: PNAS Nexus, Volumen 2, Issue 4, pgad077, 2023 &lt;br&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/pnasnexus/advance-article/doi/10.1093/pnasnexus/pgad077/7075905&#34;&gt;LINK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Urban density, in the form of residents’ and visitors’ concentration, is long considered to foster diverse exchanges of interpersonal knowledge and skills, which are intrinsic to sustainable human settlements. However, with current urban studies primarily devoted to city- and district-level analyses, we cannot unveil the elemental connection between urban density and diversity. Here we use an anonymized and privacy-enhanced mobile dataset of 0.5 million opted-in users from three metropolitan areas in the United States to show that at the scale of urban streets, density is not the only path to diversity. We represent the diversity of each street with the experienced social mixing (ESM), which describes the chances of people meeting diverse income groups throughout their daily experience. We conduct multiple experiments and show that the concentration of visitors only explains 26% of street-level ESM. However, adjacent amenities, residential diversity, and income level account for 44% of the ESM. Moreover, using longitudinal business data, we show that streets with an increased number of food businesses have seen an increased ESM from 2016 to 2018. Lastly, although streets with more visitors are more likely to have crime, diverse streets tend to have fewer crimes. These findings suggest that cities can leverage many tools beyond density to curate a diverse and safe street experience for people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great streets: visualization of the main results &lt;a href=&#34;http://greatstreets.mit.edu&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;http://greatstreets.mit.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A city is not a static tree: understanding urban areas through the lens of real-time behavioral data</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-02-24-a-city-is-not-a-static-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-02-24-a-city-is-not-a-static-tree/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Authors&lt;/em&gt;:Esteban Moro &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Publication&lt;/em&gt;: ZARCH, &lt;b&gt;19&lt;/b&gt;, 28–39. 2023 &lt;br&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.26754/ojs_zarch/zarch.2022197407&#34;&gt;LINK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Cities are the main ground on which our society and culture develop today and will evolve in the future. Against the traditional understanding of cities as physical spaces mostly around our neighborhoods, recent use of large-scale mobility datasets has enabled the study of our behavior at unprecedented spatial and temporal scales, much beyond our static residential spaces. Here we show how it is possible to use these datasets to investigate the role that human behavior plays in traditional urban problems like segregation, public health, or epidemics. Apart from measuring or monitoring such problems in a more comprehensive way, the analysis of those large datasets using modern machine learning techniques or causality detection permits to unveil of the behavioral roots behind them. As a result, only by incorporating real-time behavioral data can we design more efficient policies or interventions to improve such critical societal issues in our urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobility patterns are associated with experienced income segregation in large US cities</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-07-31-mobility-patterns-are-associated-with-experienced-income-segregation-in-large-us-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-07-31-mobility-patterns-are-associated-with-experienced-income-segregation-in-large-us-cities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Authors&lt;/em&gt;: Esteban Moro, Dan Calacci, Xiaowen Dong &amp;amp; Alex Pentland.
&lt;em&gt;Publication&lt;/em&gt;: Nature Communications 12, 4633 (2021). &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-24899-8&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Traditional understanding of urban income segregation is largely based on static coarse grained residential patterns. However, these do not capture the income segregation experience implied by the rich social interactions that happen in places that may relate to individual choices, opportunities, and mobility behavior. Using a large-scale high-resolution mobility data set of 4.5 million mobile phone users and 1.1 million places in 11 large American cities, we show that income segregation experienced in places and by individuals can differ greatly even within close spatial proximity. To further understand these ﬁne-grained income segregation patterns, we introduce a Schelling extension of a well-known mobility model, and show that experienced income segregation is associated with an individual’s tendency to explore new places (place exploration) as well as places with visitors from different income groups (social exploration). Interestingly, while the latter is more strongly associated with demographic characteristics, the former is more strongly associated with mobility behavioral variables. Our results suggest that mobility behavior plays an important role in experienced income segregation of individuals. To measure this form of income segregation, urban researchers should take into account mobility behavior and not only residential patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Segregated interactions in urban and online space</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-07-10-segregated-interactions-in-urban-and-online-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-07-10-segregated-interactions-in-urban-and-online-space/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Authors&lt;/em&gt;: Xiaowen Dong , Alfredo J. Morales, Eaman Jahani, Esteban Moro, Bruno Lepri, Burcin Bozkaya, Carlos Sarraute, Yaneer Bar-Yam and Alex Pentland &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Publication&lt;/em&gt;: EPJ Data Science &lt;b&gt;9&lt;/b&gt;, Article number: 20 &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1140/epjds/s13688-020-00238-7&#34;&gt;LINK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Urban income segregation is a widespread phenomenon that challenges societies across the globe. Classical studies on segregation have largely focused on the geographic distribution of residential neighborhoods rather than on patterns of social behaviors and interactions. In this study, we analyze segregation in economic and social interactions by observing credit card transactions and Twitter mentions among thousands of individuals in three culturally different metropolitan areas. We show that segregated interaction is amplified relative to the expected effects of geographic segregation in terms of both purchase activity and online communication. Furthermore, we find that segregation increases with difference in socio-economic status but is asymmetric for purchase activity, i.e., the amount of interaction from poorer to wealthier neighborhoods is larger than vice versa. Our results provide novel insights into the understanding of behavioral segregation in human interactions with significant socio-political and economic implications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Atlas of Inequality</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-02-the-atlas-of-segregation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-02-the-atlas-of-segregation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Segregation is hurting our societies and specially our cities. But economic inequality isn&amp;rsquo;t just limited to neighborhoods. The restaurants, stores, and other places we visit in cities are all unequal in their own way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlas of Inequality  shows the income inequality of people who visit different places in the Boston metro area. It uses aggregated anonymous location data from digital devices to estimate people&amp;rsquo;s incomes and where they spend their time. Using that data, we&amp;rsquo;ve made our own place inequality metric to capture how unequal the incomes of visitors to each place are. Economic inequality isn&amp;rsquo;t just limited to neighborhoods; it&amp;rsquo;s part of the places you visit every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it yourself here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://inequality.media.mit.edu&#34;&gt;The Atlas of Inequality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlas of Inequality is a project from the Human Dynamics group at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://media.mit.edu&#34;&gt;MIT Media Lab&lt;/a&gt; and the Department of Mathematics at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uc3m.es&#34;&gt;Universidad Carlos III de Madrid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is part of a broader initiative to understand human behavior in our cities and how large-scale problems like transportation, housing, segregation, or inequality depend in part on the emergent patterns of people’s individual opportunities and choices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>