<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nutrition on </title>
    <link>https://estebanmoro.org/tags/nutrition/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nutrition on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://estebanmoro.org/tags/nutrition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of mobile food environments on fast food visits</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-09-22-you-are-where-you-eat-effect-of-mobile-food-environments-on-fast-food-visits/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-09-22-you-are-where-you-eat-effect-of-mobile-food-environments-on-fast-food-visits/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Authors&lt;/em&gt;: Bernardo Garcia-Bulle, Abigail L. Horn, Brooke M. Bell, Mohsen Bahrami, Burcin Bozkaya, Alex Pentland, Kayla de la Haye, and Esteban Moro&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Publication&lt;/em&gt;: Nature Communications &lt;strong&gt;15&lt;/strong&gt;, article number: 2291. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-46425-2&#34;&gt;LINK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Poor diets are a leading cause of morbidity and mortality. Exposure to low-quality food environments saturated with fast food outlets is hypothesized to negatively impact diet. However, food environment research has predominantly focused on static food environments around home neighborhoods and generated mixed findings. In this work, we leverage population-scale mobility data in the U.S. to examine 62M people’s visits to food outlets and evaluate how food choice is influenced by the food environments people are exposed to as they move through their daily routines. We find that a 10% increase in exposure to fast food outlets in mobile environments increases individuals’ odds of visitation by 20%. Using our results, we simulate multiple policy strategies for intervening on food environments to reduce fast-food outlet visits. This analysis suggests that optimal interventions are informed by spatial, temporal, and behavioral features and could have 2x to 4x larger effect than traditional interventions focused on home food environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://news.northeastern.edu/2024/03/15/fast-food-location-health-impact/&#34;&gt;Efforts to limit fast-food near homes need rethinking&lt;/a&gt;, Northeastern Global News.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.news-medical.net/news/20240318/Study-reveals-daily-food-environment-exposure-shapes-fast-food-habits.aspx&#34;&gt;Study reveals daily food environment exposure shapes fast food habits&lt;/a&gt; News Medical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://dornsife.usc.edu/news/stories/fast-food-choices-revealed-by-smartphone-data/&#34;&gt;New research shows “you are what… or rather… where you eat”&lt;/a&gt; USC Dornsife News and Events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral-network determinants of health outcomes.</title>
      <link>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-10-25-behavioral-network-determinants-of-health-outcomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://estebanmoro.org/post/2022-10-25-behavioral-network-determinants-of-health-outcomes/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Our behavior conditions our health. Exposure to infections depends on our and other people’s mobility. Exposure to healthy environments or habits depends on our choices and opportunities. Although human behavior is highly adaptive and dynamic, most social determinants of health are restricted to static aggregated representations of socio-demographic groups or residential environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have started a program to understand behavioral-network determinants of health outcomes by modeling physical exposure between people and environments using large datasets of human mobility and activity and multilayer networks. For example, using mobility data and state-of-the-art epidemiological models, we built high-resolution temporal contact networks at the population scale. Having a direct link to human behavior allowed us to model and predict potential behavioral interventions (closing of venues, re-opening, quarantine, contact tracing) or the role of super-spreading events and settings in the propagation of the virus , or even analyze future trade-offs between the epidemic and economic dimensions of the pandemic. People’s movements also condition the food environments they are exposed to, impacting their diet and related disease. Most of the focus has been on static food environments around the home, such as food deserts. We use large datasets of human mobility and causal techniques to detect the food environments people are exposed to and food outlets they visit as they move through the day and study the time-dependent effect of food environments on more healthy dietary choices. By incorporating the intertwined effect between mobility, human behavior, and exposure to food environments, we can build more efficient interventions to promote healthier options and diets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent papers
&lt;small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Effect of mobile food environments on fast food visits&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What is the influence of the places we visit/work/shop on our dietary choices? We find that effect is large, but not everybody is affected by the environment equally. As a result we can design better policies to change environments and increase consumption of healthy food among different socio-demographic groups&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Bernardo Garcia-Bulle, Abigail L Horn, Brooke M Bell, Mohsen Bahrami, Burcin Bozkaya, Alex Pentland, Kayla de la Haye, Esteban Moro&lt;br&gt;
Nature Communications &lt;strong&gt;15&lt;/strong&gt; 2291 (2024)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://estebanmoro.org/pdf/Effect_of_mobile_food_environments_on_fast_food_visits.pdf&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-46425-2&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;Journal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-popover=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;2&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41467-024-46425-2&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; data-hide-less-than=&#34;10&#34;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Population mobility data provides meaningful indicators of fast food intake and diet-related diseases in diverse populations&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We use mobility data to investigate if visits to fast-food places can be use to get better understanding of who consume fast food in urban areas. We find that mobility data is a better predictor of diet-related diseases in communities than traditional surveys.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Abigail L. Horn, Brooke M. Bell, Bernardo Garcia Bulle Bueno, Mohsen Bahrami, Burcin Bozkaya, Yan Cui, John P. Wilson, Alex Pentland, Esteban Moro, Kayla de la Haye&lt;br&gt;
NPJ Digital Medicine &lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt; 208 (2023)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://estebanmoro.org/pdf/Population_mobility_data_provides_meaningful_indicators_of_fast_food_intake_and_diet_related_diseases_in_diverse_populations.pdf&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41746-023-00949-x&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;Journal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-popover=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;2&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41746-023-00949-x&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; data-hide-less-than=&#34;10&#34;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Quantifying the importance and location of SARS-CoV-2 transmission events in large metropolitan areas&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Using massive mobility data and high-resolution contact matrices we investigate who, when, and where was infected by COVID-19 in major urban areas in the US. We find that infection paths where very different across cities and that super-spreading events were prevalent but not important to explain the majority of infections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Alberto Aleta, David Martin-Corral, Michiel A. Bakker, Ana Pastore y Piontti, Marco Ajelli, Maria Litvinova, Matteo Chinazzi, Natalie E. Dean, M. Elizabeth Halloran, Ira M. Longini, Alex Pentland, Alessandro Vespignani, Yamir Moreno, Esteban Moro&lt;br&gt;
Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences &lt;strong&gt;119&lt;/strong&gt; e2112182119 (2022)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://estebanmoro.org/pdf/Quantifying_the_importance_and_location_of_SARS_CoV_2_transmission_events_in_large_metropolitan_areas.pdf&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/doi/abs/10.1073/pnas.2112182119&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;Journal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-popover=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;2&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1073/pnas.2112182119&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; data-hide-less-than=&#34;10&#34;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Effect of COVID-19 response policies on walking behavior in US cities&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Ruth F. Hunter, Leandro Garcia, Thiago Herick de Sa, Belen Zapata-Diomedi, Christopher Millett, James Woodcock, Alex ‘Sandy’ Pentland, Esteban Moro&lt;br&gt;
Nature Communications &lt;strong&gt;12&lt;/strong&gt; 3652 (2021)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://estebanmoro.org/pdf/Effect_of_COVID_19_response_policies_on_walking_behavior_in_US_cities.pdf&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-021-23937-9&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;Journal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-popover=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;2&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41467-021-23937-9&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; data-hide-less-than=&#34;10&#34;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modelling the impact of testing, contact tracing and household quarantine on second waves of COVID-19&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Alberto Aleta, David Martin-Corral, Ana Pastore y Piontti, Marco Ajelli, Maria Litvinova, Matteo Chinazzi, Natalie E. Dean, M. Elizabeth Halloran, Ira M. Longini Jr, Stefano Merler, Alex Pentland, Alessandro Vespignani, Esteban Moro, Yamir Moreno&lt;br&gt;
Nature Human Behaviour &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt; 964–971 (2020)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://estebanmoro.org/pdf/Modelling_the_impact_of_testing__contact_tracing_and_household_quarantine_on_second_waves_of_COVID_19.pdf&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-020-0931-9&#34; class=&#34;BUTTON_JEL&#34;&gt;Journal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-popover=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;2&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41562-020-0931-9&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; data-hide-less-than=&#34;10&#34;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>