<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>inequality on </title>
    <link>http://estebanmoro.org/tags/inequality/</link>
    <description>Recent content in inequality on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://estebanmoro.org/tags/inequality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Using human mobility data to quantify experienced urban inequalities</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-02-26-using-human-mobility-data-to-quantify-experienced-urban-inequalities/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2025-02-26-using-human-mobility-data-to-quantify-experienced-urban-inequalities/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Fengli Xu, Qi Wang, Esteban Moro, Arianna Salazar Miranda, Marta C. González, Chaoming Song, Carlo Ratti, Luis Bettencourt, James Evans
Publication: Nature Human Behavior (2025) LINK
Abstract: The lived experience of urban life is shaped by personal mobility through dynamic relationships and resources, marked not only by access and opportunity, but also inequality and segregation. The recent availability of fine-grained mobility data and context attributes ranging from venue type to demographic mixture offer researchers a deeper understanding of experienced inequalities at scale, and pose many new questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Population mobility data provides meaningful indicators of fast food intake and diet-related diseases in diverse populations</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-11-20-population-mobility-data-provides-meaningful-indicators-of-fast-food-intake-and-diet-related-diseases-in-diverse-populations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-11-20-population-mobility-data-provides-meaningful-indicators-of-fast-food-intake-and-diet-related-diseases-in-diverse-populations/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Abigail L. Horn, Brooke M. Bell, Bernardo Garcia Bulle Bueno, Mohsen Bahrami, Burcin Bozkaya, Yan Cui, John P. Wilson, Alex Pentland, Esteban Moro, Kayla de la Haye
Publication: NPJ Digital Medicine 6, 208 (2023)
LINK
Abstract: The characteristics of food environments people are exposed to, such as the density of fast food (FF) outlets, can impact their diet and risk for diet-related chronic disease. Previous studies examining the relationship between food environments and nutritional health have produced mixed findings, potentially due to the predominant focus on static food environments around people’s homes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral changes during the COVID-19 pandemic decreased income diversity of urban encounters</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-21-behavioral-changes-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-decreased-income-diversity-of-urban-encounters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2023-04-21-behavioral-changes-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-decreased-income-diversity-of-urban-encounters/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Takahiro Yabe, Bernardo García Bulle Bueno, Xiaowen Dong, Alex Pentland &amp;amp; Esteban Moro
Publication: Nature Communications volume 14, Article number: 2310 (2023) LINK
Abstract: Diversity of physical encounters in urban environments is known to spur economic productivity while also fostering social capital. However, mobility restrictions during the pandemic have forced people to reduce urban encounters, raising questions about the social implications of behavioral changes. In this paper, we study how individual income diversity of urban encounters changed during the pandemic, using a large-scale, privacy-enhanced mobility dataset of more than one million anonymized mobile phone users in Boston, Dallas, Los Angeles, and Seattle, across three years spanning before and during the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral roots of inequality</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-behavioral-fundations-of-inequality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-02-02-behavioral-fundations-of-inequality/</guid>
      <description>Inequality is one of the most important problems in our societies. For example, economic inequality is today higher than it was in the 1970’s and by some metrics stands at levels not seen since the last Great Depression. A special form of segregation is that happening in our cities. We share the public places, our workplaces and our residential neighborhoods with people like us: same type of jobs, same education, similar economic status, and political opinions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News or social media? Socio-economic divide of mobile service consumption</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-12-01-news-or-social-media-socio-economic-divide-of-mobile-service-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2021-12-01-news-or-social-media-socio-economic-divide-of-mobile-service-consumption/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Iñaki Ucar, Marco Gramaglia, Marco Fiore, Zbigniew Smoreda, and Esteban Moro Publication: J. R. Soc. Interface (2021). Link
Abstract: Reliable and timely information on socio-economic status and divides is critical to social and economic research and policing. Novel data sources from mobile communication platforms have enabled new cost-effective approaches and models to investigate social disparity, but their lack of interpretability, accuracy or scale has limited their relevance to date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Segregated interactions in urban and online space</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-07-10-segregated-interactions-in-urban-and-online-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2020-07-10-segregated-interactions-in-urban-and-online-space/</guid>
      <description>Authors: Xiaowen Dong , Alfredo J. Morales, Eaman Jahani, Esteban Moro, Bruno Lepri, Burcin Bozkaya, Carlos Sarraute, Yaneer Bar-Yam and Alex Pentland Publication: EPJ Data Science 9, Article number: 20 LINK
Abstract: Urban income segregation is a widespread phenomenon that challenges societies across the globe. Classical studies on segregation have largely focused on the geographic distribution of residential neighborhoods rather than on patterns of social behaviors and interactions. In this study, we analyze segregation in economic and social interactions by observing credit card transactions and Twitter mentions among thousands of individuals in three culturally different metropolitan areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Atlas of Inequality</title>
      <link>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-02-the-atlas-of-segregation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://estebanmoro.org/post/2019-03-02-the-atlas-of-segregation/</guid>
      <description>Segregation is hurting our societies and specially our cities. But economic inequality isn&amp;rsquo;t just limited to neighborhoods. The restaurants, stores, and other places we visit in cities are all unequal in their own way.
The Atlas of Inequality shows the income inequality of people who visit different places in the Boston metro area. It uses aggregated anonymous location data from digital devices to estimate people&amp;rsquo;s incomes and where they spend their time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
